<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Economics | The Guardian</title>
    <link>https://www.theguardian.com/business/economics</link>
    <description>Latest news and features from theguardian.com, the world's leading liberal voice</description>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <copyright>Guardian News and Media Limited or its affiliated companies. All rights reserved. 2016</copyright>
    <pubDate>Thu, 17 Nov 2016 13:33:47 GMT</pubDate>
    <dc:date>2016-11-17T13:33:47Z</dc:date>
    <dc:language>en-gb</dc:language>
    <dc:rights>Guardian News and Media Limited or its affiliated companies. All rights reserved. 2016</dc:rights>
    <image>
      <title>The Guardian</title>
      <url>https://assets.guim.co.uk/images/guardian-logo-rss.c45beb1bafa34b347ac333af2e6fe23f.png</url>
      <link>https://www.theguardian.com</link>
    </image>
    <item>
      <title>Ed Balls calls for Bank of England reforms; Yellen hints at rate hike  – business live</title>
      <link>https://www.theguardian.com/business/live/2016/nov/17/ed-balls-bank-of-england-independence-bank-reforms-retail-sales-janet-yellen-business-live</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Former Shadow chancellor and Strictly Come Dancing contestant says better political oversight needed to address ‘popular discontent’ against central banks&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/live/2016/nov/17/ed-balls-bank-of-england-independence-bank-reforms-retail-sales-janet-yellen-business-live?page=with:block-582daaf3e4b090fc81281ead#block-582daaf3e4b090fc81281ead"&gt;Latest: Janet Yellen testifies to Congress&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/live/2016/nov/17/ed-balls-bank-of-england-independence-bank-reforms-retail-sales-janet-yellen-business-live?page=with:block-582d5cd7e4b03207800c2de4#block-582d5cd7e4b03207800c2de4"&gt;Balls writes paper on central banks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/live/2016/nov/17/ed-balls-bank-of-england-independence-bank-reforms-retail-sales-janet-yellen-business-live?page=with:block-582d583ce4b090fc81281cc0#block-582d583ce4b090fc81281cc0"&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/live/2016/nov/17/ed-balls-bank-of-england-independence-bank-reforms-retail-sales-janet-yellen-business-live?page=with:block-582d6adae4b06ac41294e7fe#block-582d6adae4b06ac41294e7fe"&gt;Balls: Central banks should give up some political independence&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Ex-MP tells Today Programme that more accountability needed&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://t.co/sVVKXUSFW8"&gt;Read his academic paper here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-17T13:22:00.790Z"&gt;1.22pm &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Janet Yellen will also tell Congress that America’s economy has made “further progress this year”.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;She begins her testimony by pointing out that the unemployment rate is now just 4.9%, with around 180,000 new jobs created each month in 2016.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Further employment gains may well help support labor force participation as well as wage gains; indeed, there are some signs that the pace of wage growth has stepped up recently.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After rising at an annual rate of just 1 percent in the first half of this year, inflation-adjusted gross domestic product is estimated to have increased nearly 3 percent in the third quarter. In part, the pickup reflected some rebuilding of inventories and a surge in soybean exports.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In addition, consumer spending has continued to post moderate gains, supported by solid growth in real disposable income, upbeat consumer confidence, low borrowing rates, and the ongoing effects of earlier increases in household wealth&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-17T13:16:11.564Z"&gt;1.16pm &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Janet Yellen&lt;/strong&gt; is pretty clear that the Fed is close to raising rates:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At our meeting earlier this month, the Committee judged that the case for an increase in the target range had continued to strengthen and that such an increase could well become appropriate relatively soon if incoming data provide some further evidence of continued progress toward the Committee’s objectives.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;BREAKING: Janet Yellen says Fed rate hike could come "relatively soon" &lt;a href="https://t.co/vEHHqfgdB7"&gt;https://t.co/vEHHqfgdB7&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://t.co/QOah76QrXP"&gt;pic.twitter.com/QOah76QrXP&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-17T13:12:44.498Z"&gt;1.12pm &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Breaking: Federal Reserve chair Janet Yellen has warned that it would be a mistake to leave US interest rates unchanged for too long.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It’s a hint that borrowing costs could be raised soon, possibly at the Fed’s next meeting in December.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Were the FOMC to delay increases in the federal funds rate for too long, it could end up having to tighten policy relatively abruptly to keep the economy from significantly overshooting both of the Committee’s longer-run policy goals. Moreover, holding the federal funds rate at its current level for too long could also encourage excessive risk-taking and ultimately undermine financial stability.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The FOMC continues to expect that the evolution of the economy will warrant only gradual increases in the federal funds rate over time to achieve and maintain maximum employment and price stability.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-17T12:36:43.245Z"&gt;12.36pm &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Bank of England is actually closer to a model modern central bank than either the US Federal Reserve or the European Central Bank, according to today’s report anyway.&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here’s the scorecard:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The FSOC...provides a forum for different regulators to challenge the Fed’s views of risks to financial stability and, because it is chaired by the Treasury, it can confer important political legitimacy for contentious regulatory decisions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-17T11:56:05.222Z"&gt;11.56am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Today’s report argues that central banks and governments need to work more closely when interest rates have reached rock bottom (the zero lower bound).&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;That could includes showering the economy with ‘helicopter money’, if government spending cuts have created a low-inflation, low-growth quagmire.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Many economists have argued that recent austerity has not improved fiscal positions much, and may even have worsened them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rather, there is reason to believe that fiscal policy is structurally prone to undermine monetary policy at the zero lower bound. Indeed, many governments also responded with austerity in the Depression, the last time that western economies fell into a liquidity trap.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-17T11:24:06.155Z"&gt;11.24am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So much for my prediction that Ed Balls wouldn’t be able to perform any dance moves on the radio....&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Yes, this is a video of &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/edballs"&gt;@edballs&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/bbcstrictly"&gt;@bbcstrictly&lt;/a&gt; fame teaching &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/bbcnickrobinson"&gt;@bbcnickrobinson&lt;/a&gt; Gangnam style during the eight o'clock news &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/r4today?src=hash"&gt;#r4today&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://t.co/yptk5Qf1uj"&gt;pic.twitter.com/yptk5Qf1uj&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-17T11:22:54.314Z"&gt;11.22am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ed Balls’ research on central banks is getting some attention this morning, thanks to the Strictly effect.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Political journalist Iain Martin reckons Balls made a good argument on the Today Programme this morning (&lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/live/2016/nov/17/ed-balls-bank-of-england-independence-bank-reforms-retail-sales-janet-yellen-business-live?page=with:block-582d6adae4b06ac41294e7fe#block-582d6adae4b06ac41294e7fe"&gt;highlights are here&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Another storming performance from &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/edballs"&gt;@edballs&lt;/a&gt; - calls for more political accountability for BoE. Seven!!! Maybe even eight.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DuncanWeldon"&gt;@DuncanWeldon&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/edballs"&gt;@edballs&lt;/a&gt; The paper is interesting. The headlines, however, are misleading. They imply an attack on independence.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/BBCr4today"&gt;@BBCr4today&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/bbcnickrobinson"&gt;@bbcnickrobinson&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/edballs"&gt;@edballs&lt;/a&gt; We need to reduce power of &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/bankofengland"&gt;@bankofengland&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hmtreasury"&gt;@hmtreasury&lt;/a&gt; - should be servants of Govt, not masters.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/guardiannews"&gt;@guardiannews&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/edballs"&gt;@edballs&lt;/a&gt; it's independence is the only reason why we can borrow so cheap twinkle toes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-17T10:59:12.905Z"&gt;10.59am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bloomberg have also covered the Balls paper, and point out that other experts are calling for central bank reforms:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former U.S. Treasury Secretary Larry Summers has said that central bank independence, conceived as a way to stop governments from stoking inflation with measures designed to gain electoral support, is an outdated concept.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Governments and monetary policy makers need to cooperate to ensure the maximum effectiveness of stimulus in a world where demand is chronically deficient, he said in a speech at the International Monetary Fund this month.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-17T10:26:31.800Z"&gt;10.26am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Here’s my colleague, Angela Monaghan, on Ed Balls’ central banking paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/bankofenglandgovernor"&gt;Bank of England&lt;/a&gt; has become too powerful in the aftermath of the financial crisis and must be reined in, according to the former shadow chancellor Ed Balls.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“I think the case for independent central banks is as strong as it’s ever been. At a time of economic uncertainty but also great political risk, we need the [US] Fed and the &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/bankofenglandgovernor"&gt;Bank of England&lt;/a&gt; to play these roles. But the reforms we’ve seen over the last few years have hugely concentrated power in central banks. I think it’s unfinished business...&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Ed Balls: Bank of England's independence should be reined in &lt;a href="https://t.co/NHA65Eq3cg"&gt;https://t.co/NHA65Eq3cg&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-17T09:52:04.527Z"&gt;9.52am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ed Balls is effectively criticising some of the reforms made by his old rival George Osborne.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In 1997, the new Labour government handed control of interest rates to the Bank of England, under a ‘tripartite’ system where financial stability was also handled by the Financial Services Authority and the Treasury.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;There's history here: when Labour made Bank independent it shared financial stability job with Treasury, FSA. (1/3) &lt;a href="https://t.co/zMxytZ43xg"&gt;https://t.co/zMxytZ43xg&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;That system was deemed to have failed in the '08 crisis - no one knew who was "driving the bus" (2/3)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;So Osborne reforms concentrated more power in hands of Bank, and &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/glitterballs?src=hash"&gt;#glitterballs&lt;/a&gt;, author of Labour's plans, thinks it's gone too far. (3/3)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-17T09:34:18.872Z"&gt;9.34am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Newsflash: UK retail sales jumped by 1.9% during October, the biggest monthly rise since July.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On an annual basis, consumers bought 7.4% more stuff than in October 2015, which is the biggest rise since April 2002.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-17T09:26:11.159Z"&gt;9.26am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;European credit strategist Tomas Hirst&lt;/strong&gt; argues that governments have caused the furore over central bank independence, by failing to use their tax and spending powers better:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Easier way of saying this is that fiscal powers need to stop passing the buck to CBs. Independence debate is really about fiscal failure. &lt;a href="https://t.co/afZ2Z3uqdo"&gt;https://t.co/afZ2Z3uqdo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-17T08:58:40.169Z"&gt;8.58am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ed Balls is also arguing that central banks should welcome more political accountability, as it would protect them in the next financial crisis&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The former shadow chancellor told the Today programme that:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If in the end when things start to go wrong, everything is concentrated in the Bank of England only, that is politically quite dangerous for the Bank.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So, in order to protect independence, the Bank needs more political support and accountability.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It’s very worrying seeing Mark Carney being attacked.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-17T08:41:13.505Z"&gt;8.41am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Former shadow chancellor Ed Balls has told the Today Programme that central bank independence is ‘unfinished’ business -- and that no country has the perfect central bank set-up yet.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He pointed out that central bankers have played a vital role since the financial crisis struck; but now have an awful lot of power: &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Over the last five years, we have hugely relied on central banks on both sides of the Atlantic to sustain growth, to keep our economies growing, and yet at the same time they’re under big attack. In Congress, the Fed being heavily criticised. We’ve seen not just MPs attacking Mark Carney and the Bank of England, but even our Prime Minister a few weeks ago slapping Mark Carney down.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I think the case for independent central banks is as strong as it’s ever been. At a time of economic uncertainty but also great political risk, we need the Fed and the Bank of England to play these roles and we don’t want them to be politically criticised, but, the reforms we’ve seen over the last few years have hugely concentrated power in central banks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It’s good to have a financial policy committee making decisions about our whole financial system, but frankly, there’s not sufficient accountability, there’s not a clear target, they’re making [decisions] that are quite distributionally politically sensitive.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If things go wrong, then politicians would have to step in and say there’s a gap in the system. What we need is a systemic risk body chaired by the chancellor, which is overseeing the whole system and setting a mandate for the Bank of England and also there if a crisis starts to build, that’s a gap we need to fill.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The low interest rate policy over the last few years is the only thing that has stopped our economy slipping back into depression. They’ve been trying to meet a target for low inflation, they’ve been undershooting because of the deflation forces in the economy. They’ve been doing their job. We actually say, what we need to have is a better dialogue between central banks and governments. If government had done a bit more work to support the economy through infrastructure spending, that would have made it easier for the Bank of England.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-17T08:30:49.490Z"&gt;8.30am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/live/2016/nov/17/ed-balls-bank-of-england-independence-bank-reforms-retail-sales-janet-yellen-business-live?page=with:block-582d5cd7e4b03207800c2de4#block-582d5cd7e4b03207800c2de4"&gt;Ed Balls’s paper on central bank independence&lt;/a&gt; comes at a good time, and not just because he’s still hanging on in Strictly.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Disenchantment with central bankers has been growing steadily; as opponents question whether keeping interest rates close to zero and pumping up asset prices was actually working.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.ft.com/content/8d52615e-a82a-11e6-8898-79a99e2a4de6"&gt;Concerns about central bank policies&lt;/a&gt; and over-reach span the political horizon. They range from president-elect Donald Trump’s accusations that the Fed kept short-term interest rates low at the behest of the Obama administration, Brexiters’ complaints that the BoE’s interventions in the debate over leaving the EU were “beneath the dignity” of the venerable institution and German politicians’ rage at the European Central Bank’s actions.&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Most complaints in the US have come from the political right. But in Britain there have been as many from the left. In setting up a review of the BoE, the leadership of the Labour party has questioned whether the central bank should be forced to fund infrastructure projects.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Admit it, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Strictly?src=hash"&gt;#Strictly&lt;/a&gt; fans, this is the &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/edballs"&gt;@edballs&lt;/a&gt; story you *really* want to read &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/SCD?src=hash"&gt;#SCD&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://t.co/PudLcVTPsJ"&gt;https://t.co/PudLcVTPsJ&lt;/a&gt; via &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/FT"&gt;@FT&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-17T08:12:19.676Z"&gt;8.12am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ed Balls is now presenting his paper on the Today programme.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He’s arguing that central bank independence must be maintained, but with additional political accountability.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;"I think the case for independent central banks is as strong as it has ever been," says &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/edballs"&gt;@edballs&lt;/a&gt; after publication of his paper &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/r4today?src=hash"&gt;#r4today&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;. &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/edballs"&gt;@edballs&lt;/a&gt; says Theresa May "slapped down" Governor of the Bank of England. Argues banks shd be independent but need more accountability&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;"Low interest rate policy is only thing that has stopped economy moving into depression." Don't then attack Bank for dong that &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/edballs"&gt;@edballs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-17T08:00:54.017Z"&gt;8.00am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;After months of delighting, or horrifying, the nation with his dancing skills, Ed Balls has sashayed back to the world of economics by arguing that the independence of the Bank of England should be curbed.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Absolutist interpretations of complete central bank independence may both undermine the pursuit of new central bank objectives and fray the political support that currently exists for central bank autonomy in their core monetary policy function.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Indeed, popular discontent towards central banks is growing in the US, UK and the euro-zone. We need a more nuanced approach to central bank independence in this brave new world.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;The &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/edballs"&gt;@edballs&lt;/a&gt; paper on central bank independence is very good - &lt;a href="https://t.co/Cm9JazQmUl"&gt;https://t.co/Cm9JazQmUl&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After the centralisation of prudential regulation – both of the micro and macro variety – and systemic risk monitoring inside the Bank of England, there is a danger that the UK money-credit constitution is too concentrated in the central bank, leading to the possibility of groupthink, a lack of oversight and ultimately risks to central bank independence.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A body, chaired by the Chancellor of the Exchequer, which provides a forum for different regulators to share information, opinions and challenge the central bank perspective. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The recent US election, and the resulting Republican control of Congress as well as the White House, are widely expected to lead to further criticism of the power and independence of the Federal Reserve. Meanwhile, in recent weeks we have seen increasingly open political attacks on Bank of England Governor Mark Carney from Brexit supporters.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But we are clear that this is no time to throw the baby out with the bathwater....&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Dance star branches out with surprising views on central bank independence. &lt;a href="https://t.co/sVVKXUSFW8"&gt;https://t.co/sVVKXUSFW8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-17T07:30:56.072Z"&gt;7.30am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Good morning, and welcome to our rolling coverage of the world economy, the financial markets, the eurozone and business.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today we’ll be watching the UK retail sales figures, at 9.30am, to see if British consumers are still shrugging off the Brexit vote.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Our European opening calls:&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/search?q=%24FTSE&amp;amp;src=ctag"&gt;$FTSE&lt;/a&gt; 6774 +0.36%&lt;br&gt;$DAX&amp;nbsp;10682 +0.17%&lt;br&gt;$CAC&amp;nbsp;4507 +0.13%&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/search?q=%24IBEX&amp;amp;src=ctag"&gt;$IBEX&lt;/a&gt; 8652 +0.16%&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/search?q=%24MIB&amp;amp;src=ctag"&gt;$MIB&lt;/a&gt; 16596 +0.22%&lt;/p&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/live/2016/nov/17/ed-balls-bank-of-england-independence-bank-reforms-retail-sales-janet-yellen-business-live"&gt;Continue reading...&lt;/a&gt;</description>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/business">Business</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/bankofenglandgovernor">Bank of England</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/janet-yellen">Janet Yellen</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/edballs">Ed Balls</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/economics">Economics</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/politics">Politics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Nov 2016 13:22:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.theguardian.com/business/live/2016/nov/17/ed-balls-bank-of-england-independence-bank-reforms-retail-sales-janet-yellen-business-live</guid>
      <media:content width="140" url="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/2e63063c870eb39ca52d6852c3d85569ee7e3481/0_132_3500_2100/master/3500.jpg?w=140&amp;q=55&amp;auto=format&amp;usm=12&amp;fit=max&amp;s=0425a516b6e595aea1f7032f4d128ba1">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Photograph: Guy Levy/BBC/PA</media:credit>
      </media:content>
      <media:content width="460" url="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/2e63063c870eb39ca52d6852c3d85569ee7e3481/0_132_3500_2100/master/3500.jpg?w=460&amp;q=55&amp;auto=format&amp;usm=12&amp;fit=max&amp;s=b0ff74108c13bfcb10c503d8a62fd87a">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Photograph: Guy Levy/BBC/PA</media:credit>
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>Graeme Wearden</dc:creator>
      <dc:date>2016-11-17T13:22:00Z</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Obama meets Merkel in Berlin to discuss TTIP and Russia in wake of Trump win</title>
      <link>https://www.theguardian.com/world/2016/nov/17/barack-obama-angela-merkel-ttip-russia-berlin-meeting-us-germany</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;US president and German chancellor have argued for US-EU trade deal and called for continued transatlantic cooperation&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Barack Obama will meet Angela Merkel in Berlin to talk about Russian sanctions, the fight against Islamic State and the future of the EU-US trade agreement in the aftermath of Donald Trump’s election victory. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The final leg of the US president’s last trip to Europe began on Wednesday night with a three-hour dinner at Hotel Adlon with the German chancellor, who he has described as &lt;a draggable="true" href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2016/nov/17/germany-daunted-by-great-expectations-as-obama-passes-baton-to-merkel"&gt;“my closest international partner”&lt;/a&gt; during his eight-year presidency.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;span&gt;Related: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2016/nov/17/germany-daunted-by-great-expectations-as-obama-passes-baton-to-merkel"&gt;Germany daunted by great expectations as Obama passes baton to Merkel&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2016/nov/17/barack-obama-angela-merkel-ttip-russia-berlin-meeting-us-germany"&gt;Continue reading...&lt;/a&gt;</description>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/world/angela-merkel">Angela Merkel</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/world/germany">Germany</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/barack-obama">Barack Obama</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/world/europe-news">Europe</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/us-news">US news</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/world/world">World news</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/us-foreign-policy">US foreign policy</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/ttip">TTIP</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/world/russia">Russia</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/business">Business</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/donaldtrump">Donald Trump</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/internationaltrade">International trade</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/global-economy">Global economy</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/economics">Economics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Nov 2016 12:38:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.theguardian.com/world/2016/nov/17/barack-obama-angela-merkel-ttip-russia-berlin-meeting-us-germany</guid>
      <media:content width="140" url="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/18ec1239fd0fd2f4db5afb71e50c7460b3458d0f/0_190_2472_1483/master/2472.jpg?w=140&amp;q=55&amp;auto=format&amp;usm=12&amp;fit=max&amp;s=d2e3719f9b9617aec16e8e7555024d43">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Photograph: Rainer Jensen/AFP/Getty Images</media:credit>
      </media:content>
      <media:content width="460" url="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/18ec1239fd0fd2f4db5afb71e50c7460b3458d0f/0_190_2472_1483/master/2472.jpg?w=460&amp;q=55&amp;auto=format&amp;usm=12&amp;fit=max&amp;s=fbc42e27cdafd9cb42f3c1694697caf8">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Photograph: Rainer Jensen/AFP/Getty Images</media:credit>
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>Philip Oltermann in Berlin</dc:creator>
      <dc:date>2016-11-17T12:38:55Z</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UK retail sales surge due to colder weather and Halloween</title>
      <link>https://www.theguardian.com/business/2016/nov/17/uk-retail-sales-halloween-brexit-inflation</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Consumers remain defiant in face of Brexit uncertainty and signs that era of low inflation may be ending&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A rush to buy winter clothes and buoyant Halloween trade for supermarkets helped UK retail sales grow at the fastest pace for 14 years in October.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.ons.gov.uk/businessindustryandtrade/retailindustry/bulletins/retailsales/oct2016"&gt;Official figures&lt;/a&gt; chimed with other indicators suggesting consumers have &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/2016/nov/08/cinemas-pubs-winter-clothes-consumer-spending-barclaycard"&gt;largely shrugged off the Brexit vote&lt;/a&gt; and defied &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/2016/mar/24/uk-retail-spending-experiences-biggest-slump-since-1991"&gt;gloomy predictions before the EU referendum&lt;/a&gt;. The volume of retail sales rose by 7.4% last month compared with a year ago, the strongest growth since early 2002.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;span&gt;Related: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/2016/nov/16/black-friday-uk-warning-report-half-offers-real-deal-pricing"&gt;Black Friday warning as report finds only half of offers are the real deal&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/2016/nov/17/uk-retail-sales-halloween-brexit-inflation"&gt;Continue reading...&lt;/a&gt;</description>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/retail">Retail industry</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/economics">Economics</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/consumerspending">Consumer spending</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/business">Business</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/uk/uk">UK news</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Nov 2016 11:05:12 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.theguardian.com/business/2016/nov/17/uk-retail-sales-halloween-brexit-inflation</guid>
      <media:content width="140" url="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/0e49cc837024d7f5578e7a1bd197488dde00cbce/0_72_2592_1555/master/2592.jpg?w=140&amp;q=55&amp;auto=format&amp;usm=12&amp;fit=max&amp;s=88e0fbe2c3d8abd0a035a0f51801d724">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Photograph: Amer Ghazzal/REX/Shutterstock</media:credit>
      </media:content>
      <media:content width="460" url="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/0e49cc837024d7f5578e7a1bd197488dde00cbce/0_72_2592_1555/master/2592.jpg?w=460&amp;q=55&amp;auto=format&amp;usm=12&amp;fit=max&amp;s=c9e36ff276fcbab587bebd5dffebe9cb">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Photograph: Amer Ghazzal/REX/Shutterstock</media:credit>
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>Katie Allen</dc:creator>
      <dc:date>2016-11-17T11:05:12Z</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Does this government want to punish us for being disabled? | Jane Campbell</title>
      <link>https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2016/nov/17/government-punish-us-disabled-disability-cuts</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A further £30-a-week cut to disability benefits will drive even more people into poverty, yet still the Tories maintain their defensive, Scrooge-like approach&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Politicians across the spectrum tell me of their growing concerns about the way national and local government treats disabled people and the negative effects this has on our culture. Some of those politicians will be speaking in parliament today about the government’s plans to further cut benefits from April for some disabled adults who are unable to work, due to disability or a long-term health condition. The £30-a-week cut will result in someone on an income of approximately £5,000 having to live on £3,500 a year instead. It will be nothing short of devastating.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Earlier this month the government extolled the virtues of paid employment for disabled people and those with long-term health conditions, and how it plans to help more of them get jobs. We would all applaud that, as we would their pledge to consult disabled people before deciding on how to do it. All good so far, but reflecting on the government’s recent record on disability, we should proceed with great caution.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When you’re poor, the effects are frightening and energy sapping&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;span&gt;Related: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2016/nov/08/un-report-austerity-disability-cuts-theresa-may"&gt;Our disabled community is suffering. Time to act on the UN report, not reject it | Katharine Quarmby&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2016/nov/17/government-punish-us-disabled-disability-cuts"&gt;Continue reading...&lt;/a&gt;</description>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/society/disability">Disability</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/society/benefits">Benefits</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/austerity">Austerity</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/economics">Economics</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/uk/uk">UK news</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Nov 2016 10:00:45 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2016/nov/17/government-punish-us-disabled-disability-cuts</guid>
      <media:content width="140" url="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/a1510bb340d9e3a1e5bab0eb163f94925d8bad13/0_37_4000_2400/master/4000.jpg?w=140&amp;q=55&amp;auto=format&amp;usm=12&amp;fit=max&amp;s=3dee3c0a3892307385dfb98874b0d68f">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Photograph: Vickie Flores/REX/Shutterstock</media:credit>
      </media:content>
      <media:content width="460" url="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/a1510bb340d9e3a1e5bab0eb163f94925d8bad13/0_37_4000_2400/master/4000.jpg?w=460&amp;q=55&amp;auto=format&amp;usm=12&amp;fit=max&amp;s=0847c8d8edf310966e546eb2016b6806">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Photograph: Vickie Flores/REX/Shutterstock</media:credit>
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>Jane Campbell</dc:creator>
      <dc:date>2016-11-17T10:00:45Z</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cut after cut has left a disabled woman with nothing to live on | Frances Ryan</title>
      <link>https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2016/nov/17/cut-disabled-woman-dwp</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Bessie has been hit by a succession of cruel blows by the DWP. She even ended up pawning her inherited jewellery just to eat and stay warm&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When a &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/2016/nov/07/uk-austerity-policies-amount-to-violations-of-disabled-peoples-rights"&gt;UN inquiry&lt;/a&gt; ruled last week that Britain’s austerity policies amount to a “systematic violation” of disabled people’s rights, it was talking about people like Bessie.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bessie, 51, has agoraphobia, Asperger’s and complex mental health problems, and for the last three-and-a-half years she’s lived the reality of Conservative cuts. First came the bedroom tax, taking with it £12 a week. Then she was told her lifetime disability benefit would &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2016/sep/22/we-cant-help-being-disabled-reassessment-hysteria-scroungers-cheating-system"&gt;be scrapped&lt;/a&gt;. And now, as the latest cruel blow, Bessie – who’s received out-of-work sickness benefits since 2012 – has been declared “fit for work”. “You get over one thing and then another hits,” she says quietly. “It’s horrendous.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;span&gt;Related: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/2016/nov/07/uk-austerity-policies-amount-to-violations-of-disabled-peoples-rights"&gt;UK austerity policies 'amount to violations of disabled people's rights'&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;You get over one thing and then another hits. It’s horrendous.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2016/nov/17/cut-disabled-woman-dwp"&gt;Continue reading...&lt;/a&gt;</description>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/society/disability">Disability</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/austerity">Austerity</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/economics">Economics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Nov 2016 09:00:43 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2016/nov/17/cut-disabled-woman-dwp</guid>
      <media:content width="140" url="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/7ce22a9dcd572b49f9aeadca71db9d95720a0ce7/0_16_2113_1267/master/2113.jpg?w=140&amp;q=55&amp;auto=format&amp;usm=12&amp;fit=max&amp;s=2c0450e69050c8406a8edbb8d361d388">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Photograph: Matt Cardy/Getty Images</media:credit>
      </media:content>
      <media:content width="460" url="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/7ce22a9dcd572b49f9aeadca71db9d95720a0ce7/0_16_2113_1267/master/2113.jpg?w=460&amp;q=55&amp;auto=format&amp;usm=12&amp;fit=max&amp;s=ab65248fedb77d951b5e3b297cc126db">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Photograph: Matt Cardy/Getty Images</media:credit>
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>Frances Ryan</dc:creator>
      <dc:date>2016-11-17T09:00:43Z</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The pursuit of happiness: could a ‘happy city index’ end Bristol’s blues?</title>
      <link>https://www.theguardian.com/cities/2016/nov/17/pursuit-happiness-happy-city-index-end-bristol-blues</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In a drive to see human contentment guide policymaking, a research centre in Bristol has found a way to score cities by their residents’ wellbeing. In a place which is home to some of England’s poorest areas, politicians are listening&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If there is one experience every citizen of Bristol knows well, it is the misery of trudging, sodden and panting, up a steep hill as the rain pours down on you. No word captures the feeling of grumbling discontent it inspires, and few would be foolish enough to put a number on it.&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But some Bristolians are trying to do exactly that. They have become fed up of being fed up – and as a starting point to cheering up their communities, they are trying to measure the city’s happiness in order to increase it.&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We have the opportunity ​to measure progress beyond ‘L​​et’s grow the economy’,​ which is often what we default to&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;span&gt;Related: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/cities/2016/may/23/bristol-mayor-marvin-rees-racism-inequality"&gt;Bristol mayor Marvin Rees: ‘My dad arrived to signs saying​: ​No Irish, no blacks, no dogs’&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/cities/2016/nov/17/pursuit-happiness-happy-city-index-end-bristol-blues"&gt;Continue reading...&lt;/a&gt;</description>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/cities/cities">Cities</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/uk/bristol">Bristol</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/health-and-wellbeing">Health &amp; wellbeing</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/uk/uk">UK news</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/economics">Economics</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/society/society">Society</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Nov 2016 07:00:41 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.theguardian.com/cities/2016/nov/17/pursuit-happiness-happy-city-index-end-bristol-blues</guid>
      <media:content width="140" url="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/6c44da8dc2f4f2d678f5750c9ec384e724fee5b8/0_301_5150_3090/master/5150.jpg?w=140&amp;q=55&amp;auto=format&amp;usm=12&amp;fit=max&amp;s=147ea0636c1b37217d61728d1c4d2637">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Photograph: Sean Crawford / Alamy/Alamy</media:credit>
      </media:content>
      <media:content width="460" url="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/6c44da8dc2f4f2d678f5750c9ec384e724fee5b8/0_301_5150_3090/master/5150.jpg?w=460&amp;q=55&amp;auto=format&amp;usm=12&amp;fit=max&amp;s=7ae1cfc197fc665a07ffe4f6a0eb4fb5">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Photograph: Sean Crawford / Alamy/Alamy</media:credit>
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>Ajit Niranjan</dc:creator>
      <dc:date>2016-11-17T07:00:41Z</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Justin Welby to help UK thinktank build vision of post-Brexit economy</title>
      <link>https://www.theguardian.com/uk-news/2016/nov/17/justin-welby-thinktank-ippr-build-vision-post-brexit-uk-economy</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Archbishop of Canterbury among leading figures joining two-year study by left-leaning Institute for Public Policy Research&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The archbishop of Canterbury will spend the next two years as part of a commission launched by a left-leaning thinktank that aims to rewrite the rules for Britain’s post-&lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/eu-referendum"&gt;Brexit &lt;/a&gt;economy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/uk/justin-welby"&gt;Justin Welby&lt;/a&gt; will join other leading figures including the general secretary of the TUC, Frances O’Grady, and the chairman of the John Lewis Partnership, Sir Charlie Mayfield, on the Institute for Public Policy Research (IPPR) programme that will seek remedies for six key UK weaknesses.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/uk-news/2016/nov/17/justin-welby-thinktank-ippr-build-vision-post-brexit-uk-economy"&gt;Continue reading...&lt;/a&gt;</description>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/uk/justin-welby">Justin Welby</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/eu-referendum">EU referendum and Brexit</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/economics">Economics</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/economy">Economic policy</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/society/society">Society</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/uk/uk">UK news</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/business">Business</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/politics">Politics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Nov 2016 00:01:33 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.theguardian.com/uk-news/2016/nov/17/justin-welby-thinktank-ippr-build-vision-post-brexit-uk-economy</guid>
      <media:content width="140" url="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/3cce6428fe257aecd8a27075a661a7d268dbc468/0_0_3499_2099/master/3499.jpg?w=140&amp;q=55&amp;auto=format&amp;usm=12&amp;fit=max&amp;s=707eef50aa3fc7b84ea50aadf0b5c4e3">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Photograph: Neil Hall/Reuters</media:credit>
      </media:content>
      <media:content width="460" url="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/3cce6428fe257aecd8a27075a661a7d268dbc468/0_0_3499_2099/master/3499.jpg?w=460&amp;q=55&amp;auto=format&amp;usm=12&amp;fit=max&amp;s=59a73bca71e2ea5d03bc4c12bc9fccff">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Photograph: Neil Hall/Reuters</media:credit>
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>Larry Elliott Economics editor</dc:creator>
      <dc:date>2016-11-17T00:01:33Z</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Obama and Merkel call for continued transatlantic cooperation</title>
      <link>https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2016/nov/16/barack-obama-and-angela-merkel-call-for-continued-transatlantic-cooperation</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;US president and German chancellor write joint article stressing importance of partnership on issues such as climate change and terrorism &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Outgoing US president, Barack Obama, and the German chancellor, Angela Merkel, have made an appeal for continued cooperation between the US and the European Union on climate change, anti-terror measures as well as a transatlantic trade deal during Donald Trump’s presidency.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a joint op-ed &lt;a href="http://www.wiwo.de/politik/ausland/us-wahlen/merkel-obama-papier-globalisierung-gemeinsam-gestalten-/14850600.html"&gt;published in German weekly Wirtschaftswoche&lt;/a&gt; on the eve of the president’s last European visit in office, the two leaders argue that while the world is at a crossroads, “the future is already happening and there will not be a return to a world before globalisation”.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;span&gt;Related: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2016/nov/16/obama-calls-for-course-correction-to-share-spoils-of-globalisation"&gt;Obama calls for 'course correction' to share spoils of globalisation&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2016/nov/16/barack-obama-and-angela-merkel-call-for-continued-transatlantic-cooperation"&gt;Continue reading...&lt;/a&gt;</description>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/us-news">US news</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/barack-obama">Barack Obama</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/world/angela-merkel">Angela Merkel</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/world/germany">Germany</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/world/world">World news</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/ttip">TTIP</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/business">Business</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/internationaltrade">International trade</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/global-economy">Global economy</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/economics">Economics</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/world/europe-news">Europe</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/world/globalisation">Globalisation</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Nov 2016 20:12:16 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2016/nov/16/barack-obama-and-angela-merkel-call-for-continued-transatlantic-cooperation</guid>
      <media:content width="140" url="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/57e5c5790cb2abedb7589e0e66416a2b9e70dfc8/230_45_2399_1440/master/2399.jpg?w=140&amp;q=55&amp;auto=format&amp;usm=12&amp;fit=max&amp;s=1359ae74fda78a846f65b48308839e85">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Photograph: Sean Gallup/Getty Images</media:credit>
      </media:content>
      <media:content width="460" url="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/57e5c5790cb2abedb7589e0e66416a2b9e70dfc8/230_45_2399_1440/master/2399.jpg?w=460&amp;q=55&amp;auto=format&amp;usm=12&amp;fit=max&amp;s=2def59e683a13df42d4a23ae3bd6b5b9">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Photograph: Sean Gallup/Getty Images</media:credit>
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>Philip Oltermann in Berlin</dc:creator>
      <dc:date>2016-11-16T20:12:16Z</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Guardian view on employment law: an overhaul is needed | Editorial</title>
      <link>https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2016/nov/16/the-guardian-view-on-employment-law-an-overhaul-is-needed</link>
      <description>Too many employees are no longer protected by a legal system designed for a different age&lt;p&gt;Our report that a well-qualified academic &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/uk-news/2016/nov/16/nottingham-academic-on-casual-contract-i-had-more-rights-as-a-binman" title=""&gt;once earned so little&lt;/a&gt; on his casual contract that he had to supplement it with a job as a refuse collector is confirmation that precarious work has metastasised from unskilled or elementary-level jobs to reach parts of the economy once considered the epitome of security. According to &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/uk-news/2016/nov/16/universities-accused-of-importing-sports-direct-model-for-lecturers-pay" title=""&gt;analysis of the official figures&lt;/a&gt; by the University and College Union, more than half of academics in Britain’s universities, where students are paying £9,000 a year in fees, are employed on temporary or insecure contracts. They are recruits to &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/uk-news/2016/nov/15/more-than-7m-britons-in-precarious-employment" title=""&gt;a burgeoning class of workers&lt;/a&gt;, many of them described as self-employed, that make up the “just about managing”. Ranging from agency workers in warehouses and care assistants to the top-grade professions, these are the people who Theresa May has pledged to put at the heart of her response to the Brexit revolt.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;span&gt;Related: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/uk-news/2016/nov/16/universities-accused-of-importing-sports-direct-model-for-lecturers-pay"&gt;Universities accused of 'importing Sports Direct model' for lecturers' pay&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;span&gt;Related: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/uk-news/2016/nov/15/more-than-7m-britons-in-precarious-employment"&gt;More than 7m Britons now in precarious employment&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2016/nov/16/the-guardian-view-on-employment-law-an-overhaul-is-needed"&gt;Continue reading...&lt;/a&gt;</description>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/law/employment-law">Employment law</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/hmrc">HMRC</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/uk-news/zero-hours-contracts">Zero-hours contracts</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/the-gig-economy">Gig economy</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/theresamay">Theresa May</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/philip-hammond">Philip Hammond</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/uber">Uber</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/economics">Economics</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/economy">Economic policy</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/politics">Politics</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/technology">Technology</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/education/education">Education</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/education/higher-education">Higher education</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/business">Business</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/law/law">Law</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/tradeunions">Trade unions</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/uk/uk">UK news</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/money/maternitypaternityrights">Maternity &amp; paternity rights</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/money/employeebenefits">Employee benefits</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/money/work-and-careers">Work &amp; careers</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/money/money">Money</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/tuc">TUC</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Nov 2016 19:25:14 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2016/nov/16/the-guardian-view-on-employment-law-an-overhaul-is-needed</guid>
      <media:content width="140" url="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/16bb9b7e2830db179b7fa01c362e2b0854b39fdc/0_0_5100_3060/master/5100.jpg?w=140&amp;q=55&amp;auto=format&amp;usm=12&amp;fit=max&amp;s=a9b8f28917fff1ef229ea441ae9cb77f">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Photograph: Alamy</media:credit>
      </media:content>
      <media:content width="460" url="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/16bb9b7e2830db179b7fa01c362e2b0854b39fdc/0_0_5100_3060/master/5100.jpg?w=460&amp;q=55&amp;auto=format&amp;usm=12&amp;fit=max&amp;s=f13774f0b966385bad0c7047fea12978">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Photograph: Alamy</media:credit>
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>Editorial</dc:creator>
      <dc:date>2016-11-16T19:25:14Z</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neoliberalism and other factors in the breakdown of society | Letters</title>
      <link>https://www.theguardian.com/politics/2016/nov/16/neoliberalism-and-other-factors-in-the-breakdown-of-society</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;George Monbiot concludes that, in response to the crisis that lies behind Brexit and Trump, what we need is “a new story of what it is to be a human in the 21st century” (&lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2016/nov/14/neoliberalsim-donald-trump-george-monbiot" title=""&gt;The deep story beneath Trump’s triumph&lt;/a&gt;, 14 November). What&amp;nbsp;we actually need is a revolution in our institutions of learning.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In order to solve the grave global problems we face – climate change, population growth, extinction of species, war, inequality and the rest – we need governments to act appropriately. But governments are unlikely to be much more enlightened than electorates. Hence we require the public to have a good understanding of what our problems are, and what we need to do about them. That in turn requires that universities are devoted to intelligent public education about our problems and how to solve them. At present universities, devoted primarily to the pursuit of knowledge, fail&amp;nbsp;disastrously to do what is required.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/2016/nov/16/neoliberalism-and-other-factors-in-the-breakdown-of-society"&gt;Continue reading...&lt;/a&gt;</description>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/politics">Politics</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/economics">Economics</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/donaldtrump">Donald Trump</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/tonyblair">Tony Blair</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/margaretthatcher">Margaret Thatcher</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/harold-wilson">Harold Wilson</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/eu-referendum">EU referendum and Brexit</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/us-elections-2016">US elections 2016</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/us-politics">US politics</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/us-news">US news</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/uk/uk">UK news</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/foreignpolicy">Foreign policy</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/past">Politics past</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/economy">Economic policy</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/business">Business</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/books/economics">Economics</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/books/books">Books</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Nov 2016 19:03:20 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.theguardian.com/politics/2016/nov/16/neoliberalism-and-other-factors-in-the-breakdown-of-society</guid>
      <media:content width="140" url="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/ffcae812e81ba4205cdc31da7f3647d589b1d257/0_35_2207_1324/master/2207.jpg?w=140&amp;q=55&amp;auto=format&amp;usm=12&amp;fit=max&amp;s=0e83e1c6c7e30189c3a47bc8d7ee5cb9">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Photograph: Jim Watson/AFP/Getty Images</media:credit>
      </media:content>
      <media:content width="460" url="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/ffcae812e81ba4205cdc31da7f3647d589b1d257/0_35_2207_1324/master/2207.jpg?w=460&amp;q=55&amp;auto=format&amp;usm=12&amp;fit=max&amp;s=e9882a9f29eb6c4915c7fbfa91b48c5a">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Photograph: Jim Watson/AFP/Getty Images</media:credit>
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>Letters</dc:creator>
      <dc:date>2016-11-16T19:03:20Z</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UK unemployment rate falls to 4.8% but claimant count jumps – as it happened</title>
      <link>https://www.theguardian.com/business/live/2016/nov/16/uk-unemployment-rate-wage-growth-earnings-brexit-business-live</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Britain’s jobless rate has dropped to a new 11-year low, but the number of people receiving unemployment benefit has risen by almost 10,000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/live/2016/nov/16/uk-unemployment-rate-wage-growth-earnings-brexit-business-live?page=with:block-582c7bc7e4b090fc812818b3#block-582c7bc7e4b090fc812818b3"&gt;Oil volatile but Opec deal hopes grow&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/live/2016/nov/16/uk-unemployment-rate-wage-growth-earnings-brexit-business-live?page=with:block-582c2725e4b06ac41294e187#block-582c2725e4b06ac41294e187"&gt;Jobless rate hits 11-year low&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/live/2016/nov/16/uk-unemployment-rate-wage-growth-earnings-brexit-business-live?page=with:block-582c2f09e4b090fc812816cc#block-582c2f09e4b090fc812816cc"&gt;But claimant count suggests storms ahead&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/live/2016/nov/16/uk-unemployment-rate-wage-growth-earnings-brexit-business-live?page=with:block-582c2869e4b03207800c2835#block-582c2869e4b03207800c2835"&gt;Average earnings (ex bonuses) rise by 2.4%&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/live/2016/nov/16/uk-unemployment-rate-wage-growth-earnings-brexit-business-live?page=with:block-582c29c7e4b06ac41294e198#block-582c29c7e4b06ac41294e198"&gt;The key points&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/live/2016/nov/16/uk-unemployment-rate-wage-growth-earnings-brexit-business-live?page=with:block-582c2ce1e4b06ac41294e1ac#block-582c2ce1e4b06ac41294e1ac"&gt;No cut in EU workers in Britain&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-16T17:39:15.892Z"&gt;5.39pm &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;With Wall Street falling back after several days of rises, investors were pausing for breath a week after Donald Trump’s shock victory in the US election.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The mixed picture from the UK employment data - jobless rate down, claimant count up - added to the uncertainty. But the pound held firm against the euro although it edged lower against a resurgent dollar. The US currency was boosted by the growing belief that the Federal Reserve is almost certain to raise interest rates next month, as well as the continuing expectation of a Trump spending boom. Chris Beauchamp, chief market analyst at IG, said:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The mood across most equity markets remains subdued, with modest losses being posted. Investors are evidently still cautious about the new [American] administration, with the steady drip of news relating to appointments and the like keeping the market in check. About the only thing still surging is the US dollar.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-16T17:11:15.075Z"&gt;5.11pm &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ahead of Italy’s referendum next month, there is some unwelcome analysis from S&amp;amp;P, which paints a fairly uninspiring picture of the prospects for the country’s economy. It said:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Italian economy is likely to achieve only slow growth of less than 1% of GDP per year over 2016-2018, say S&amp;amp;P Global Ratings economists in a report published today (“&lt;a href="https://www.globalcreditportal.com/ratingsdirect/showArticlePage.do?sp_mid=75191&amp;amp;sp_rid=2071633&amp;amp;object_id=9865022&amp;amp;rev_id=1&amp;amp;elqTrackId=73388d9285554dad95048fb0523f625b&amp;amp;elq=ff72ce07824e45c2bd22b179d4815176&amp;amp;elqaid=75191&amp;amp;elqat=1&amp;amp;elqCampaignId="&gt;Only A Modest Recovery In Sight For Italy&lt;/a&gt;”).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“We don’t expect the Italian economy to return to its pre-crisis output peak before the middle of the next decade because productivity remains very depressed. &lt;a href="https://www.globalcreditportal.com/ratingsdirect/entityPage.do?sp_mid=75191&amp;amp;sp_rid=2071633&amp;amp;entityId=107135&amp;amp;elqTrackId=cd1e11bd9f4640f3ab243fd182183f9c&amp;amp;elq=ff72ce07824e45c2bd22b179d4815176&amp;amp;elqaid=75191&amp;amp;elqat=1&amp;amp;elqCampaignId="&gt;Italy&lt;/a&gt; is the only European country not to have recorded any productivity gains since 2000,” said Jean-Michel Six, Chief Economist for EMEA at S&amp;amp;P Global Ratings.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-16T15:48:14.506Z"&gt;3.48pm &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Oil prices continue to be volatile, coming under pressure after &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;more evidence of growing stockpiles but then recovering.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After the American Petroleum Institute reported &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/live/2016/nov/16/uk-unemployment-rate-wage-growth-earnings-brexit-business-live?page=with:block-582c569ce4b06ac41294e2cf#block-582c569ce4b06ac41294e2cf"&gt;a higher than expected stock build &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;last week, comes a similar tale from the US Energy Information Administration.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-16T15:12:39.054Z"&gt;3.12pm &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;US president Barack Obama might be pushing for &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/live/2016/nov/16/uk-unemployment-rate-wage-growth-earnings-brexit-business-live?page=with:block-582c6556e4b090fc8128181b#block-582c6556e4b090fc8128181b"&gt;debt relief for Greece&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, but unsurprisingly Germany disagrees (which should make Obama’s upcoming meeting with Angela Merkel interesting). Reuters &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.reuters.com/article/us-eurozone-greece-debt-germany-idUSKBN13B1L7"&gt;reports&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Germany on Wednesday opposed calls for debt relief for Greece after U.S. President Barack Obama offered support for such a mechanism for the recession-hit euro zone state during a trip to Athens.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;German Finance Minister Wolfgang Schäuble said late on Tuesday granting Greece debt relief would do it a disservice.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Athens signed up to a third economic bailout package of up to 86 billion euros last year but wants long-term debt restructuring to exit its crisis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Germany, which has long said there is no immediate need for debt relief for Greece as it would discourage much-needed structural reforms, said it noted the comments from Obama, who flies to Berlin later on Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-16T14:44:24.813Z"&gt;2.44pm &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The prospect of higher US interest rates has brought an end to the rally which has seen leading US shares hit new heights.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After rising for seven straight trading sessions in the run up and aftermath of Donald Trump’s shock US presidential election victory, the Dow Jones Industrial Average is currently down 55 points or 0.3%. The S&amp;amp;P 500 opened down 0.25% while Nasdaq was 0.4% lower.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-16T14:41:34.646Z"&gt;2.41pm &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;The same sterling weakness that was made worse by the Bank Rate cut and QE of Jon Cunliffe &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/BoE?src=hash"&gt;#BoE&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/OpenMouthOperations?src=hash"&gt;#OpenMouthOperations&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://t.co/V1lp1t9sqt"&gt;https://t.co/V1lp1t9sqt&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-16T14:26:36.914Z"&gt;2.26pm &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Back with the UK, and the Bank of England’s Jon Cunliffe has said recent currency movements had made setting interest rates move difficult. Reuters &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.reuters.com/article/us-britain-boe-cunliffe-idUSKBN13B1QX"&gt;reports&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sterling’s sharp fall since Britain voted to leave the European Union has made it harder to set monetary policy, BoE Deputy Governor Jon Cunliffe said on Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cunliffe said he fully backed the central bank’s neutral stance regarding its next move in interest rates, as announced earlier this month, and its latest quarterly set of forecasts which see a modest slowdown next year.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-16T14:21:30.959Z"&gt;2.21pm &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;US industrial production figures have come in slightly worse than expected.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It was unchanged in October compared to forecasts of a 0.2% increase. The September figure was revised down from a 0.1% rise to a 0.2% fall.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/UnitedStates?src=hash"&gt;#UnitedStates&lt;/a&gt; Industrial Production month-on-month at 0.0% &lt;a href="https://t.co/if5ZbL1j2Y"&gt;https://t.co/if5ZbL1j2Y&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://t.co/UdJ8Ll5Hba"&gt;pic.twitter.com/UdJ8Ll5Hba&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-16T14:03:54.709Z"&gt;2.03pm &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On his final day in Greece, US president Barack Obama repeated his belief that debt relief was vital for the country. The Athens News Agency - Macedonian Press Agency &lt;a href="http://www.amna.gr/english/article/15933/Obamas-visit:-Greece-needs-debt-relief-because-people-need-hope--Obama-says"&gt;reports:&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking at the Stavros Niarchos Foundation on Wednesday, U.S. President Barack Obama once again highlighted the need for Greece’s creditors to agree to debt relief, in accordance with the advice of the International Monetary Fund (IMF), noting that the country, and especially its young people, needed to see hope and a future.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; “The IMF has said that debt relief will be crucial to get Greece back to growth. They are right. It is important because if reforms here are to be sustained, people here need to see hope and they need to see progress.” &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Obama giving his farewell speech lauding the virtues of &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/democracy?src=hash"&gt;#democracy&lt;/a&gt; in Athens 2day &lt;a href="https://t.co/bqyTgHU3G3"&gt;pic.twitter.com/bqyTgHU3G3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Obama at the Acropolis &lt;a href="https://t.co/KTwsMuRIGH"&gt;pic.twitter.com/KTwsMuRIGH&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;At one point in his Acropolis tour, Pres Obama was heard to ask his guide "So, how is this all financed?" The response was not heard. &lt;a href="https://t.co/iGXM6Jly6o"&gt;pic.twitter.com/iGXM6Jly6o&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Obama tours the Acropolis Museum in Athens &lt;a href="https://t.co/4lSJckXs7S"&gt;pic.twitter.com/4lSJckXs7S&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Back to reality. &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Obama?src=hash"&gt;#Obama&lt;/a&gt; leaves for Berlin. &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/obama_athens?src=hash"&gt;#obama_athens&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://t.co/sUwCYDKW04"&gt;pic.twitter.com/sUwCYDKW04&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-16T13:53:51.258Z"&gt;1.53pm &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here’s IHS Markit on the UK employment data:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/UK?src=hash"&gt;#UK&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/unemployment?src=hash"&gt;#unemployment&lt;/a&gt; rate falls to 11-year low, but uncertainty about the future continues to restrain hiring &lt;a href="https://t.co/dA2yCG5BU3"&gt;https://t.co/dA2yCG5BU3&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://t.co/vbE0lCEHUO"&gt;pic.twitter.com/vbE0lCEHUO&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-16T13:48:48.978Z"&gt;1.48pm &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Over in Europe, and the latest on the draft budgets put forward by member states. Reuters &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.reuters.com/article/us-eurozone-budgets-idUSKBN13B19P"&gt;reports&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Italy and five other countries are at risk of breaking European Union budget discipline rules with their 2017 draft budgets, the European Commission said in a statement on Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The five other countries are Belgium, Cyprus, Lithuania, Slovenia and Finland.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-16T13:14:27.765Z"&gt;1.14pm &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The pound’s renewed dip came after an early gain in the immediate aftermath of the UK unemployment figures. Chris Saint, Senior Analyst at Hargreaves Lansdown Currency Service, said:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sterling has drifted lower against the euro and US dollar during European trading hours this morning, finding itself back around the €1.16 and US$1.24 levels by midday. There was some tentative support for the pound after today’s UK labour market figures, but the gains were short-lived...On the face of it the headline numbers suggest the jobs market has remained buoyant in the first few months since the EU referendum, although the data probably does little to alter the Bank of England’s future policy path at this stage as pay growth is still relatively contained.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-16T12:57:38.973Z"&gt;12.57pm &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The stronger dollar has helped send the oil price lower, after a surge in crude on Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Talk of an informal meeting on Friday in Doha between oil producers to prepare plans for an output agreement later this month had sent crude soaring around 5% on Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-16T12:52:10.738Z"&gt;12.52pm &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The dollar continues to strengthen as the odds of a US interest rate rise next month continue to shorten.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Federal Reserve board member James Bullard is the latest to back an increase, saying that unless there are any major shocks, rates will be hiked. Given how the market has reacted to Donald Trump’s unexpected victory in the US election, it is hard to know what major shock would upset the market at this point.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The strength in the dollar index does represent a risk for the emerging markets and it can also eat into corporate profit for the US firms. The current move is also massively backed by bets that the Fed is going to raise the interest rate and odds are standing at 94%. It is important to keep in mind that come in December, it is the tone of the Fed for the future trajectory of the interest rate hike which is going to impact the dollar.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-16T12:43:38.394Z"&gt;12.43pm &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And here’s our economics editor Larry Elliott’s take on the figures:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;All things considered, the government will be happy with &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/2016/nov/16/uk-unemployment-falls-september-office-for-national-statistics"&gt;how the labour market performed in the first three months after the EU referendum&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Unemployment has continued to fall and at 4.8% of the workforce is at its lowest level for 11 years. Employment has continued to rise and there are plenty of jobs to be had. Ministers would not have expected anything better than that in the turbulent post-Brexit weeks and would have feared a much worse outcome.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;span&gt;Related: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/2016/nov/16/employment-brexit-vote-claimant-count"&gt;Employment not hit by Brexit vote –&amp;nbsp;but there may be clouds ahead&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-16T12:41:46.678Z"&gt;12.41pm &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here’s our report on the UK jobs data. Phillip Inman writes:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Unemployment dropped to its lowest level in 11 years in September in a further indication that Britain’s employers have largely shrugged off the June Brexit vote.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the first health check of the labour market covering the three months since the referendum, official figures show the unemployment rate was 4.8%, the lowest since September 2005 and down &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/2016/oct/19/uk-employment-rate-at-record-high-despite-brexit-vote"&gt;from 4.9% in August&lt;/a&gt; and 5.3% a year earlier. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;span&gt;Related: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/2016/nov/16/uk-unemployment-falls-september-office-for-national-statistics"&gt;Unemployment falls to 11-year low&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-16T12:31:31.301Z"&gt;12.31pm &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-16T12:07:47.585Z"&gt;12.07pm &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Over in parliament, Theresa May has hailed today’s unemployment figures, at Prime Minister’s Questions.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;May argues:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The unemployment figures show the strength of the fundamental of our economy&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The employment rate has never been higher, and the unemployment rate is at its lowest in a decade.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;span&gt;Related: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/blog/live/2016/nov/16/pmqs-may-corbyn-brexit-uk-wants-brexit-deal-that-is-intellectually-impossible-says-eurozone-chief-politics-live"&gt;May and Corbyn at PMQs - Politics live&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-16T11:53:45.440Z"&gt;11.53am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Several economists are concerned that British pay packets will be gnawed by inflation next year.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today’s labour market report shows that total pay rose by 2.3% over the last year, unchanged on a month earlier. That’s more than inflation, which fell to 0.9% in October.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Annual pay growth remained at 2.3% on a three-month average basis, suggesting that workers are in a weak position to offset what is likely to be a sizeable rise in inflation over the next year.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Indeed, the capacity of employers to pay more will not be supported by continued weak productivity growth. Overall, prospects of the labour market taking a turn for the worse in the not-too distant future are looking more likely.” &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Real pay growth is the slowest it’s been since early 2015. Wages are not growing fast enough to withstand the rise in inflation expected next year.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Without swift action from the government, working people could soon by paying the price for Brexit with another fall in living standards.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-16T11:23:40.239Z"&gt;11.23am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The jobless rate in Wales has inched up to 4.4%, from 4.3% a month ago, due to a 3,000 increase in unemployment.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Year on year, Wales has outperformed the rest of the UK when it comes to improvements in employment, unemployment and economic inactivity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; “Unemployment in Wales, at 4.4%, is lower than in England, Scotland or Northern Ireland and remains well below the UK average. Meanwhile the employment rate remains close to its record high, with 41,000 more people in work across Wales than at this same time last year. Unemployment amongst 18 to 24 year-olds in Wales is down 9.1% on the year and there are also 19,000 fewer people economically inactive than a year ago.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-16T11:07:07.431Z"&gt;11.07am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Professor Geraint Johnes&lt;/strong&gt;, director of research at The Work Foundation, has delved into the labour market report to find some interesting details:&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The labour market statistics indicate that the labour market remains remarkably stable. The rolling three month measure of unemployment shows a fall of some 37,000 over the most recent quarter, with the rate of unemployment now at 4.8%.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The unemployment fall has been widely distributed across the country, though there were increases in both the North West and the East. For the UK as a whole, both full-time and part-time employee numbers increased by 31000.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-16T10:55:46.222Z"&gt;10.55am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Britain’s public sector has continued to shrink, to its smallest size in at least 17 years&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today’s figures show that there were 5.33 million people employed in the public sector in June, 13,000 fewer than in March. That’s the lowest since comparable records began in 1999&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-16T10:52:46.927Z"&gt;10.52am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;John Hawksworth, chief economist at PwC,&lt;/strong&gt; also fears that unemployment will rise in 2017, even though there’s no sign of a Brexit shock yet:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Unemployment tends to be a lagging indicator, and we could yet see a modest rise in the jobless total next year as uncertainty around the Brexit negotiations dampens business investment and slows overall economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But we do not expect the UK economy to go into recession, so would not expect any large increases in unemployment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-16T10:10:36.271Z"&gt;10.10am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Several City experts are concerned that the number of Britons signing on for unemployment benefit jumped by almost 10,000 last month.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Duncan Weldon of Resolution Group says it’s an ‘early warning sign’ of problems ahead.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Headline unemployment number is v good. But backward looking.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Claimant count and tax receipts are both good early warning signs for UK outlook and neither looks good.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;I'd read slowing jobs growth as "UK near full employment" not "Brexit impact". Claimant count more concerning.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The UK’s labour market continues to surprise with its resilience to the Brexit shock. The unemployment rate fell unexpectedly to a new 11-year low of 4.8% in the three months to September. This is yet more evidence that the labour market and the wider economy have fared better than expected since June’s referendum.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, there could be storm clouds gathering on the horizon. The claimant count – which in a quirk of the data is a more recent figure than the unemployment rate – jumped by 9,800 in October, with September’s figure revised upwards from 700 to 5,600. All in all, it does seem likely that unemployment could tick up somewhat during the coming months, though dire predictions made in the immediate aftermath of the vote appear wide of the mark.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The rise in the claimant count change - which is a fairer representation of the current environment as this data point covers the period until the end of last month - takes the shine off the good news at the very least and possibly even usurps it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In rising to 9.8k, this indicator came in at its highest level since November 2012 and when you also consider the upward revision of the prior print (to 5.6k from 0.7k) this could be taken as a warning sign that everything may not be quite as rosy as it appears for the labour market.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-16T10:02:25.645Z"&gt;10.02am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ONS statistician David Freeman has sounded an important note of caution.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He points out that employment growth is slowing; just 49,000 people found work in the July-September quarter, which is the slowest rate since March.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Unemployment is at its lowest for more than ten years, and the employment rate remains at a record high. Nonetheless, there are signs that the labour market might be cooling, with employment growth slowing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;”The Labour Force Survey also includes information on the nationality and country of birth of workers. That limited evidence suggests the referendum outcome and subsequent devaluation of sterling has had little impact so far on the number of EU workers in the UK labour force.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-16T09:54:27.852Z"&gt;9.54am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Employment minister Damian Hinds has hailed the news that Britain’s unemployment rate has hit its lowest rate since July to September 2005.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hinds says:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Yet again we have a strong set of figures, with employment continuing to run at a record high and unemployment falling to an 11-year low. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Growth is being fuelled by full-time professional jobs while wages are continuing to perform strongly, which underlines the resilience of the UK labour market. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-16T09:51:52.275Z"&gt;9.51am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;New independent stats show the employment rate is the highest since records began in 1971 &lt;a href="https://t.co/H3AnLLk2oj"&gt;pic.twitter.com/H3AnLLk2oj&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today’s unemployment report shows that the number of people in work rose in the last quarter, and the number of people out of work fell.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-16T09:49:37.256Z"&gt;9.49am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Both men and women benefitted from the drop in unemployment, as this chart shows:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-16T09:39:34.676Z"&gt;9.39am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We have a small, and welcome, rise in average earnings too.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Average pay, excluding bonuses, rose by 2.4% annually in the July-September quarter, up from 2.3%.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;For Jul-Sep 2016 wages up 2.3% on a year including bonuses and 2.4% on a year excluding bonuses &lt;a href="https://t.co/akklsvf2Wc"&gt;https://t.co/akklsvf2Wc&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://t.co/b8Rj7WcLGZ"&gt;pic.twitter.com/b8Rj7WcLGZ&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-16T09:35:35.879Z"&gt;9.35am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The number of people signing on for unemployment benefit has jumped, by much more than economists expected.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The claimant count rose by 9,800 in October, the ONS reports.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-16T09:31:34.808Z"&gt;9.31am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Breaking: Britain’s unemployment rate has fallen to 4.8% in the three months to September.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;That’s a new 11-year low, down from 4.9% a month earlier.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-16T09:27:57.027Z"&gt;9.27am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Barratt Development have sent a shiver through the UK property market this morning by revealing it has cut the price of some high-end London properties, worth over £1m.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Barratt CEO David Thomas told shareholders that.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Market conditions in London at higher selling prices remain more challenging.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To mitigate these risks we have taken pricing action on a number of our sites in London.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;span&gt;Related: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/2016/nov/16/barratt-london-homes-brexit"&gt;Barratt cuts price of top London homes&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-16T09:21:28.673Z"&gt;9.21am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One of the big threats facing Britain’s labour market is the risk that City banks start to shift operations across to Europe, following the EU referendum.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“We are not planning to change anything any time soon and we will wait and see where the dust settles”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-16T08:58:06.813Z"&gt;8.58am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Over in Athens, they’re getting ready to welcome US president Barack Obama to the historic Acropolis site - by imposing a massive security clampdown in the area.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Athens?src=hash"&gt;#Athens&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Acropolis?src=hash"&gt;#Acropolis&lt;/a&gt;: site now closed off in preparation for tour by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/obama?src=hash"&gt;#obama&lt;/a&gt; on second day of visit to &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Greece?src=hash"&gt;#Greece&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/POTUS"&gt;@POTUS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Obama will in one hour visit Acropolis. City center of Athens getting ready &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/obama_athens?src=hash"&gt;#obama_athens&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/ObamaGR?src=hash"&gt;#ObamaGR&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Greece?src=hash"&gt;#Greece&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Gr%C4%8Dija?src=hash"&gt;#Grčija&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://t.co/CtyUoYqQE9"&gt;pic.twitter.com/CtyUoYqQE9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-16T08:36:01.558Z"&gt;8.36am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Oca&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;do’s share price is getting an early morning drubbing, down almost 5%.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It’s pure profit for the supermarket - the scheme is “capital light” and will contribute to a £50m-£100m incremental profit opportunity outlined in the 2015/16 preliminary results.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is a big money-spinner for Morrisons and gives it a massive edge over Tesco and Sainsbury in the home delivery market. With prices being slashed and competition fierce, this is the kind of deal that will make a big difference to the bottom line.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Morrison’s has launched a service at Amazon. Orders will delivered same day by Amazon. What role Ocado&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-16T08:27:36.614Z"&gt;8.27am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;There’s no drama in the financial markets this morning.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Both the unemployment rate and wage growth readings are forecast to remain unchanged at 2.3% (though it could creep a bit higher to 2.4%) and 4.9% respectively; the jobless claims figure, on the other hand, is set to see a bit more movement, rising to 1,900 from the 700 seen the month previous.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-16T08:16:36.401Z"&gt;8.16am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RBC Capital Markets believe Britain’s unemployment rate may have actually fallen in the July-September quarter to 4.8%, a new 11-year low.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;That would cause much celebration on Downing Street, I’m sure. But it doesn’t mean that next year won’t be tough, RBC say:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The unemployment rate could actually fall this month to 4.8% from 4.9%. The headline rate is the average of the last three single-month estimates and with the last two months both printing at 4.7% it looks highly likely that we see a tick down by one-tenth.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This does though feel more like a short-term quirk than reflective of the outlook where a more challenging macroeconomic outlook in 2017 should put some modest upward pressure on unemployment. Accordingly our expectation for the range of employment gains over the last three months is 60-100k as a central case.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We’re looking for unemployment and wage growth both to be pretty unchanged, which wouldn’t provide any obvious support for the pound.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-16T07:59:15.343Z"&gt;7.59am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Good morning, and welcome to our rolling coverage of the world economy, the financial markets, the eurozone and business.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;span&gt;Related: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2016/nov/15/barack-obama-raises-possibility-of-debt-relief-on-final-greece-visit"&gt;Barack Obama raises possibility of debt relief on final Greece visit&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/live/2016/nov/16/uk-unemployment-rate-wage-growth-earnings-brexit-business-live"&gt;Continue reading...&lt;/a&gt;</description>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/stock-markets">Stock markets</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/business">Business</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/society/unemployment">Unemployment</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/uk-unemployment-and-employment-statistics">UK unemployment and employment statistics</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/unemployment-and-employment-statistics">Unemployment and employment statistics</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/economics">Economics</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Nov 2016 17:39:15 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.theguardian.com/business/live/2016/nov/16/uk-unemployment-rate-wage-growth-earnings-brexit-business-live</guid>
      <media:content width="140" url="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/e0d044cb688f9b7fe13d5fbf9cf3b5d9b76d20f6/0_230_5660_3395/master/5660.jpg?w=140&amp;q=55&amp;auto=format&amp;usm=12&amp;fit=max&amp;s=0bf5f7bf0ec4fe2ffca0de28c21fdfe6">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Photograph: Geoff Robinson Photography/REX</media:credit>
      </media:content>
      <media:content width="460" url="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/e0d044cb688f9b7fe13d5fbf9cf3b5d9b76d20f6/0_230_5660_3395/master/5660.jpg?w=460&amp;q=55&amp;auto=format&amp;usm=12&amp;fit=max&amp;s=c31a92b3697fec61522171d913682ddc">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Photograph: Geoff Robinson Photography/REX</media:credit>
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>Graeme Wearden (until 12.35) and Nick Fletcher</dc:creator>
      <dc:date>2016-11-16T17:39:15Z</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UK investment in tech and transport among world's worst, says TUC</title>
      <link>https://www.theguardian.com/business/2016/nov/16/uk-investment-tech-transport-tuc-autumn-statement</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Study will put pressure on Philip Hammond to boost spending across public and private sectors in autumn statement&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Britain ranks among the worst performers in the developed world for spending on new technology, industrial machinery and transport equipment, according to a study by the TUC of investment spending in the public and private sectors.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The UK came 34th out of the 34 members of the Organisation for Economic Cooperation &amp;amp; Development (OECD) for spending on transport equipment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;span&gt;Related: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/uk-news/2016/nov/15/uk-tax-cuts-pwc-philip-hammond-autumn-statement-gdp-growth"&gt;UK slowdown will give chancellor little scope for tax cuts, says PwC&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/2016/nov/16/uk-investment-tech-transport-tuc-autumn-statement"&gt;Continue reading...&lt;/a&gt;</description>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/technology">Technology sector</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/economics">Economics</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/business">Business</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/tuc">TUC</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/economy">Economic policy</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/uk-news/autumn-statement-2016">Autumn statement 2016</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/politics">Politics</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/uk/uk">UK news</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Nov 2016 06:01:11 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.theguardian.com/business/2016/nov/16/uk-investment-tech-transport-tuc-autumn-statement</guid>
      <media:content width="140" url="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/d3521379de7ab29940880b15490ce0d1a78b010b/0_0_5184_3110/master/5184.jpg?w=140&amp;q=55&amp;auto=format&amp;usm=12&amp;fit=max&amp;s=a0876f33aab31f93c505087c69b89fab">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Photograph: Christopher Furlong/Getty Images</media:credit>
      </media:content>
      <media:content width="460" url="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/d3521379de7ab29940880b15490ce0d1a78b010b/0_0_5184_3110/master/5184.jpg?w=460&amp;q=55&amp;auto=format&amp;usm=12&amp;fit=max&amp;s=bf7e485fd9c04562e043ec188b5a131c">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Photograph: Christopher Furlong/Getty Images</media:credit>
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>Phillip Inman Economics correspondent</dc:creator>
      <dc:date>2016-11-16T06:01:11Z</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hammond urged to protect poorest from long-term rise in inflation</title>
      <link>https://www.theguardian.com/business/2016/nov/15/uk-inflation-rate-dips-to-09</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Chancellor gets surprise boost as UK inflation rate dips to 0.9% but analysts expect cost of living to climb as rising costs feed through to consumers&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Philip Hammond was on Tuesday being urged to ignore a small and unexpected fall in inflation and use next week’s autumn statement to protect Britain’s poorest families from an expected sharp rise in the cost of living in 2017.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The chancellor was provided with a boost ahead of his first set-piece occasion on November 23 when cheaper clothes and a smaller increase in university tuition fees meant the annual increase in the cost of living as measured by the &lt;a href="https://www.ons.gov.uk/economy/inflationandpriceindices/bulletins/consumerpriceinflation/oct2016"&gt;consumer prices index&lt;/a&gt; fell from 1% to 0.9%.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;span&gt;Related: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/live/2016/nov/15/german-growth-uk-inflation-mark-carney-bond-market-obama-greece-business-live"&gt;UK inflation rate drops to 0.9% – business live&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/2016/nov/15/uk-inflation-rate-dips-to-09"&gt;Continue reading...&lt;/a&gt;</description>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/inflation">Inflation</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/economicgrowth">Economic growth (GDP)</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/economy">Economic policy</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/business">Business</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/politics">Politics</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/economics">Economics</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/uk/uk">UK news</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/manufacturing-sector">Manufacturing sector</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/retail">Retail industry</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/uk/office-for-national-statistics">Office for National Statistics</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/sterling">Sterling</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/currencies">Currencies</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/philip-hammond">Philip Hammond</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Nov 2016 23:37:17 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.theguardian.com/business/2016/nov/15/uk-inflation-rate-dips-to-09</guid>
      <media:content width="140" url="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/801a07d3efe4e0562bc998130295afad6656bb6b/0_20_4252_2552/master/4252.jpg?w=140&amp;q=55&amp;auto=format&amp;usm=12&amp;fit=max&amp;s=c4e4e0258d7a90d6479e63b67baa0a05">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Photograph: Nick Ansell/PA</media:credit>
      </media:content>
      <media:content width="460" url="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/801a07d3efe4e0562bc998130295afad6656bb6b/0_20_4252_2552/master/4252.jpg?w=460&amp;q=55&amp;auto=format&amp;usm=12&amp;fit=max&amp;s=81896b908412bf97931e48c29ea3c382">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Photograph: Nick Ansell/PA</media:credit>
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>Larry Elliott Economics editor</dc:creator>
      <dc:date>2016-11-15T23:37:17Z</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mark Carney: central banks not to blame for rising inequality - as it happened</title>
      <link>https://www.theguardian.com/business/live/2016/nov/15/german-growth-uk-inflation-mark-carney-bond-market-obama-greece-business-live</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BoE governor says central banks aren’t solely responsible for rising inequality and record low interest rates, as he insists he’ll leave in 2019&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/live/2016/nov/15/german-growth-uk-inflation-mark-carney-bond-market-obama-greece-business-live?page=with:block-582b1c23e4b0eb4ebf2744d4#block-582b1c23e4b0eb4ebf2744d4"&gt;President Obama in Greece&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/live/2016/nov/15/german-growth-uk-inflation-mark-carney-bond-market-obama-greece-business-live?page=with:block-582b1563e4b05c05c52f5441#block-582b1563e4b05c05c52f5441"&gt;Stronger than expected US retail sales&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/live/2016/nov/15/german-growth-uk-inflation-mark-carney-bond-market-obama-greece-business-live?page=with:block-582b101ee4b05c05c52f5419#block-582b101ee4b05c05c52f5419"&gt;Mark Carney faces MPs: What we learned&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/live/2016/nov/15/german-growth-uk-inflation-mark-carney-bond-market-obama-greece-business-live?page=with:block-582ae7c6e4b05c05c52f52d3#block-582ae7c6e4b05c05c52f52d3"&gt;Carney: Critics are conducting a massive blame deflection game&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/live/2016/nov/15/german-growth-uk-inflation-mark-carney-bond-market-obama-greece-business-live?page=with:block-582ae29ae4b0eb4ebf27435b#block-582ae29ae4b0eb4ebf27435b"&gt;Carney quizzed by the Treasury committee&lt;/a&gt;: highlights start here&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/live/2016/nov/15/german-growth-uk-inflation-mark-carney-bond-market-obama-greece-business-live?page=with:block-582ad3e1e4b05c05c52f5269#block-582ad3e1e4b05c05c52f5269"&gt;UK inflation drops to 0.9%&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-15T18:11:15.025Z"&gt;6.11pm &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The weaker than expected UK inflation figures have put pressure on the pound again, pushing it lower against the dollar and the euro.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sterling is currently down 0.4% at $1.2433 against the dollar, and the same amount lower against the euro at €1.1585.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-15T17:30:25.750Z"&gt;5.30pm &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Despite the Dow Jones Industrial Average slipping back after several days of gains, European markets ended the day in positive territory. The UK market was helped by weaker than expected inflation figures, which pushed back the chances of an interest rate rise from the Bank of England. Joshua Mahony, market analyst at IG, said:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Stock markets rose once more today, as hopes of a high growth period based on substantial fiscal stimulus continued to stoke the embers of last week’s US election... we have seen energy stocks grab some respite today, as crude prices rose in the wake of a fresh charge from OPEC to find a means to ensure the output cut comes to fruition.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-15T17:01:07.415Z"&gt;5.01pm &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Elsewhere, crude has been buoyed by renewed talk that oil producers are trying to pave the way for an agreement on curbing output later this month. Brent crude is currently up 4% at $46.24 a barrel while West Texas Intermediate has jumped 4.4% to $45.24.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reuters has reported that Saudi energy minister Khalid al-Falih is expected to travel to Qatar this week for a meeting with producers. The outline of a deal to limit output was agreed by Opec in Algiers in September, but the details have proved difficult to agree.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-15T16:55:33.452Z"&gt;4.55pm &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not everyone is happy with Barack Obama’s presence in Greece. Helena Smith reports:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thousands of protestors have taken to the streets in a mass display of opposition against Obama.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Despite a government ban on protestors taking place during the 29-hour period the US president is expected to be in the Greek capital as many as 3,000 people, many communists and hardline leftists, have defied the order to gather in central Athens and march towards the US embassy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-15T15:40:01.601Z"&gt;3.40pm &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here are Obama and Alexis Tsipras, courtesy of the White House, with the US president saying he would continue to urge Greece’s creditors to take the steps needed to put the country on the path to a durable economic recovery:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;"Kalispera." Watch &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/POTUS"&gt;@POTUS&lt;/a&gt; speak alongside PM &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/tsipras_eu"&gt;@tsipras_eu&lt;/a&gt; in Athens—his first stop on his final planned foreign trip: &lt;a href="https://t.co/BDXY7VdZmH"&gt;https://t.co/BDXY7VdZmH&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-15T15:11:39.589Z"&gt;3.11pm &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After six straight days of rises, the Dow Jones Industrial Average is pausing for breathe.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is currently down 26 points or 0.15%, but the S&amp;amp;P 500 and Nasdaq both moved higher at the open.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-15T15:09:38.829Z"&gt;3.09pm &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;More from Obama on debt relief for Greece:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Obama?src=hash"&gt;#Obama&lt;/a&gt;: it is important to combine reforms, cuts with growth agenda &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Greece?src=hash"&gt;#Greece&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Obama?src=hash"&gt;#Obama&lt;/a&gt;: you need a growth agenda, difficult without debt relief mechanism &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Greece?src=hash"&gt;#Greece&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;"Elex always turn on personalities .. turn on natural desire for change if incumbant has been there for 8 years," says &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Obama?src=hash"&gt;#Obama&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Athens?src=hash"&gt;#Athens&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Tsipras says he is *optimistic* that Merkel will be convinced (by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/POTUS"&gt;@POTUS&lt;/a&gt; !) to provide substantive debt relief to Greece. &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/obama_athens?src=hash"&gt;#obama_athens&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-15T14:49:38.417Z"&gt;2.49pm &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And here are Obama’s comments. Helena reports:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“I have always wanted to come to Greece ... I think we all know that the world owes an enormous debt to Greece and the Greek people,” Obama also told reporters.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“The ideas of ancient Greeks helped inspire our founding fathers ….to this day the United States is profoundly grateful to our Greek friends.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-15T14:44:21.921Z"&gt;2.44pm &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Back to Greece again, where the US president has begun his farewell tour of Europe. Our correspondent Helena Smith reports:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Barack Obama may be visiting Athens at the end of his time in office but the outgoing US leader has not disappointed. Barely three hours after he touched down in a Greek capital rendered almost unrecognizable by draconian security, Obama said the three words Greek officials have wanted the world leader to utter: debt, austerity and solidarity. “I will continue to underline that austerity alone cannot deliver prosperity,” he told the Greek prime minister Alexis Tsipras after being greeted by the debt-stricken country’s head of state and the rousing tones of a military honour band. “Debt relief is needed.” &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Earlier he had said: “Greece has gone through very challenging and dramatic times over the last several years. We are glad to see that progress is being made, although we recognise that there are significant challenges ahead, and we intend to stand shoulder to shoulder with the Greek people throughout this process. “ &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Athens’ leftist led government has made little secret that it hopes the US president’s open display of support will resonate with Germany and other partners in Europe which have footed the bill of the nation’s massive bailouts but demanded punishing belt-tightening in return. “We consider this visit will contribute to the effort to reduce Greece’s debt, its spokesman said ahead of the leader’s arrival. “The US president has repeatedly stated he wants to solve this huge issue before he leaves office.” &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Obama, only the fourth American leader to visit the country since its foundation nearly 200 years ago, heads to Berlin once his 29-hour sojourn in Athens ends on Wednesday. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Obama, who also spoke of the importance of reforms in making the Greek economy more competitive, emphasized the significance of a “strong, prosperous and unified Europe … not just for the people of Europe but for the whole world and the US.” &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is the first time a sitting US president has elected to visit Greece on its own. On previous occasions Turkey has also been included in the tour. But Obama, who is accompanied by his Secretary of Treasury Jack Lew and Assistant Secretary of State for European and Eurasian Affairs Victoria Nuland, is believed to have wanted to make the trip for a long time. “It was a personal choice,” said the defense minister Panos Kammenos speaking to a local radio station after welcoming the leader at Athens’ international airport. The symbolism of Athens being the birthplace of democracy also played a significant role for a president now determined to allay the fears of European leaders following the election of his successor Donald Trump last week.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At a press conference following 90-minute talks with Obama, the Greek prime minister said it was vital that Greeks began to feel the effects of the sacrifices they have made in recent years. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“After seven years the Greek people cannot bear any more austerity,” he told reporters. “Greece deserves debt relief and the time is now. President Obama and I discussed a number of issues specifically the important potential of investment in Greece and the future of Greece with its shipping power becoming an important centre for trade, transport and energy.” &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-15T14:41:31.039Z"&gt;2.41pm &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But the signs of US economic strength question the need for any fiscal stimulus, says Dr Harm Bandholz, chief US economist at UniCredit Research:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The consumption strength (and the related good performance of the US economy in the second half of 2016) has important policy implications.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;First, and most straightforward, it allows the Fed to stay on course for a rate hike at the upcoming meeting in mid-December.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-15T14:36:11.276Z"&gt;2.36pm &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The strong US retail sales figures have only added to the expectation that the US Federal Reserve will raise interest rates in December. Rob Carnell, chief international economist at ING Bank, said a hike next month was almost in the bag:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Strong US retail sales, and an expectation of further gains in inflation (due out on November 17) make the 92% market probability for a 14 December Fed rate hike look about right (nothing is 100% until it is done).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not only were headline retail sales figures strong at +0.8% month on month, but there were strong core figures (control group which strips out the more volatile items also rose 0.8% month on month). The figures were stronger than the consensus expected (+0.6% month on month), and stronger still when upwards revisions to the previous months’ data are taken into account.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-15T14:21:32.028Z"&gt;2.21pm &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;While Mark Carney was delighting MPs by doling out party invitations, the US released better than forecast retail sales figures for October.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.census.gov/retail/index.html"&gt;the Commerce Department,&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; retail sales rose 0.8% last month compared to September, with a particularly strong performance from the car industry. On top of that, building materials were also in demand, perhaps due to households hit by Hurricane Matthew having to rebuild and repair damage. The year on year rise was 4.3%.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-15T14:16:37.889Z"&gt;2.16pm &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mark Carney was on rather jolly form as he faced MPs today, perhaps happy that the issue of his term length was finally resolved last month. But what did we actually learn?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; I think it is very important to distinguish between the stance of monetary policy and the reasons why global interest rates are low, the reasons why inequality have increased across major economies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The last two are caused by much more fundamental factors and an excessive focus on monetary policy in many respects is a massive blame deflection exercise.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is a practical reality, which is I’ll be separated from my family for that extra period of extension so there are limits, reasonable limits to what that would be.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I will leave June 30th 2019.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Inflation is going up.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The pass through from a 20 percent fall in the trade weighted level of sterling is going to come,it’s going to build towards the end of this year into 2017 and in our expectation, be above 2 percent by the middle of 2017 and stay there for a while because of that pass through.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If the time to exit is measured in 18 months or less and the degree of exit is viewed as considerable then a number of those firms would take decisions, that’s the best guidance I can give.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-15T13:39:29.940Z"&gt;1.39pm &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mark Carney ends the meeting by returning to his theme that there is a “blame exercise” underway&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;, with central banks being labelled as the only cause of problems in the economy today.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He says that only politicians can really tackle inequality - his job is to help create economic stability and stable inflation.&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We’re going to have to run exeptionally loose monetary policy&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We are going to continually make clear that we can’t make the structural changes that will drive productivity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;*CARNEY: IT WOULD BE WELCOME TO RAISE INTEREST RATES&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-15T13:33:14.848Z"&gt;1.33pm &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;And finally, Steve Baker tries to get himself swiftly dis-invited &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/live/2016/nov/15/german-growth-uk-inflation-mark-carney-bond-market-obama-greece-business-live?page=with:block-582b05a3e4b05c05c52f53c8#block-582b05a3e4b05c05c52f53c8"&gt;from the Bank of England Christmas party&lt;/a&gt;, by asking:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q: Have you lost the plot?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I do not accept the line of thought that central banks should not focus on their remit. They should tighten policy in order to force governments to take tough decisions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;That’s straying from the mandate. That’s political.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-15T13:18:05.898Z"&gt;1.18pm &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rees-Mogg&lt;/strong&gt; asks whether the Bank’s latest (more optimistic) economic forecasts will affect economic growth, in the same way that Mark Carney’s statement immediately after the Brexit vote helped shore up confidence (in the bank’s view, anyway)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Tiptoeing carefully, Carney suggests that forecast changes don’t have as much impact on consumers as actual interest rate changes (or commitments to act).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-15T13:07:04.039Z"&gt;1.07pm &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Finally, Jacob Rees-Mogg gets to question the Bank of England.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rees-Mogg is one of Mark Carney’s toughest critics, and recently suggested the governor should resign for his comments before the Brexit vote.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;BREAKING: Mark Carney has invited arch nemesis Jacob Rees-Mogg to the Bank of England's Xmas party&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-15T12:54:53.756Z"&gt;12.54pm &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mark Carney has challenged politicians to implement ‘major’ structural economic reforms.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Otherwise, we could be stuck with low interest rates for decades.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;*CARNEY: LOW-RATE TRAP MAY PERSIST DECADES UNLESS MAJOR REFORMS&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;BOE Gov &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Carney?src=hash"&gt;#Carney&lt;/a&gt;: monetary policy is not "loose"; global equilibrium interest rates low &amp;amp; could be "trapped" here for decades without reforms&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-15T12:48:40.028Z"&gt;12.48pm &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mark Carney&lt;/strong&gt; says that only 4% of companies with a pension deficit say that current low interest rates are causing a problem.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q: But you at the Bank of England have just boosted the contributions into your own final salary scheme, says Helen Goodman.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-15T12:40:22.575Z"&gt;12.40pm &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Back in parliament, Helen Goodman MP challenges the Bank of England over its QE scheme.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q: By pushing down bond yields, you’ve damaged defined benefit pension schemes and forced them to put more money to cover deficits,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-15T12:32:12.959Z"&gt;12.32pm &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Breaking away from Mark Carney.... over in Greece, president Barack Obama has arrived in Athens.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Security is extra right in the Greek capital; there’s a complete lockdown, with protests banned, public transport stopped, schools closed down,.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Air Force One touches down in &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Athens?src=hash"&gt;#Athens&lt;/a&gt; for &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/obama_athens?src=hash"&gt;#obama_athens&lt;/a&gt; visit&lt;br&gt;(screen shot from ERT Pool via &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/AP"&gt;@AP&lt;/a&gt; Direct) &lt;a href="https://t.co/6zNUOXgBvO"&gt;pic.twitter.com/6zNUOXgBvO&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Obama arrives in Greece at start of his final foreign tour &lt;a href="https://t.co/WrLutOiwcV"&gt;https://t.co/WrLutOiwcV&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://t.co/BmDsm6UpqC"&gt;pic.twitter.com/BmDsm6UpqC&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Happening now: Obama meets with Greece's president in Athens on his final foreign tour &lt;a href="https://t.co/ygETv07JFa"&gt;pic.twitter.com/ygETv07JFa&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Obama and Tsipras sit down &lt;a href="https://t.co/MUNHfto5Rd"&gt;pic.twitter.com/MUNHfto5Rd&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-15T12:24:15.286Z"&gt;12.24pm &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Andrew Tyrie takes Carney back to the slump in sterling since the Brexit vote, and tries to get him to admit that a weak pound is a good thing.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q: Was the fall in the exchange rate welcome?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Carney ought to say: given the revision down in our expected future income, and the increased riskiness of the UK, fall in £ was inevitable&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;And to have fought against it with monetary policy would have triggered a recession. That's the answer to Tyrie's question.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-15T12:20:08.879Z"&gt;12.20pm &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mark Carney hands out a brief economics lesson, insisting that the relationship between the money supply and inflation is ‘non-existant’.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Some of the MPs look unconvinced; maybe remembering Margaret Thatcher’s zeal for monetarism (which encouraged her government to hike interest rates and trigger the deep recession of the early 80s).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-15T12:05:34.326Z"&gt;12.05pm &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Carney says there’s no ‘precise number’ that shows the limit of the Bank’s tolerance for higher inflation (&lt;em&gt;so no new forward guidance today!&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It all depends why inflation is moving - including whether the public’s inflation expectations have risen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-15T11:51:53.391Z"&gt;11.51am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Carney says that inflation in October was lower than expected (&lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/live/2016/nov/15/german-growth-uk-inflation-mark-carney-bond-market-obama-greece-business-live?page=with:block-582ad3e1e4b05c05c52f5269#block-582ad3e1e4b05c05c52f5269"&gt;as we covered this morning&lt;/a&gt;) mainly due to short-term effects in the clothing market.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But... he insists that inflation is going to rise in the months ahead, as the weaker pound pushes up the price of imported goods.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Mark Carney, asked by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/RachelReevesMP"&gt;@RachelReevesMP&lt;/a&gt; why falling £ &amp;amp; rising import prices weren't yet feeding into much higher inflation: "It's coming"&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Carney?src=hash"&gt;#Carney&lt;/a&gt;: inflation rises to 2% by mid 2017 due to weak Pound: 60% passes thru to producer prices over 6-9 mos, longer to hit consumer prices&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Carney is talking about pass throughs from sterling to inflation by referencing toblerones. Well done everyone.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-15T11:43:32.041Z"&gt;11.43am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Boom! &lt;/strong&gt;Mark Carney suggests that City firms could start executing plans to leave London in autumn 2017, if they are disappointed by the early shape of the government’s Brexit deal.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He tells the committee:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If the time to exit is measured in 18 months, or less, and the degree of exit is considerable, then a number of firms will take decisions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;CARNEY SAYS WHEN TIME TO EXIT EU IS 18 MTHS &amp;amp; IMPACT OF BREXIT IS CONSIDERABLE, THEN FINANCIAL SERVICES FIRMS MAY TRIGGER CONTINGENCY PLANS&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-15T11:37:36.800Z"&gt;11.37am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q: What steps is Britain’s financial sector taking for Brexit?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Carney says that firms in the core of the financial sector, such as banks and insurance firms, are making contingency plans.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As they follow those plans, hard decisions will be taken.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But I would stress, to those firms, that it is very early days. So planning makes sense, action is in general precipitous.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-15T11:33:49.090Z"&gt;11.33am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Our view is that it’s still early days [for Brexit]”, Mark Carney says.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Article 50 hasn’t been triggered yet, and we don’t know if there will be a transition period afterwards.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-15T11:30:32.661Z"&gt;11.30am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wes Streeting MP takes Mark Carney into the details of Brexit.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Carney says that the financial markets have taken a more downbeat view of Brexit than consumers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-15T11:24:10.841Z"&gt;11.24am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sky News’s Ed Conway &lt;/strong&gt;makes an important point -- &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/live/2016/nov/15/german-growth-uk-inflation-mark-carney-bond-market-obama-greece-business-live?page=with:block-582ae29ae4b0eb4ebf27435b#block-582ae29ae4b0eb4ebf27435b"&gt;until this morning&lt;/a&gt;, we didn’t know that former chancellor George Osborne had asked Mark Carney to serve three more years.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Carney reveals &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/George_Osborne"&gt;@George_osborne&lt;/a&gt; asked him earlier this year to extend his term to a full eight years&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-15T11:23:13.757Z"&gt;11.23am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;John Mann: How can the Bank of England plan for Brexit when no-one knows what it will mean?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We certainly don’t know what the eventual shape of Brexit will be, agrees MPC member Michael Saunders. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-15T11:14:31.863Z"&gt;11.14am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;John Mann MP now challenges Mark Carney over the composition of his monetary policy committee.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q: Wouldn’t a trade union economist being some much-needed industry experience, to help the Bank understand the economy.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-15T11:12:13.799Z"&gt;11.12am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Andrew Tyrie jabs at Carney, suggesting he’s uttering ‘Delphic’ words over forward guidance. &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The guidance is that there isn’t any guidance, right?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Tyrie tells Mark Carney central bankers are guilty of "Delphic utterances". "Your capacity to create a theology is boundless" &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-15T11:05:19.305Z"&gt;11.05am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conservative MP &lt;a href="http://www.parliament.uk/biographies/commons/kit-malthouse/4495"&gt;Kit Malthouse&lt;/a&gt; asks Mark Carney to explain the position with forward guidance (the governor’s famous policy of pledging not to raise interest rates until the economy has reached a certain point).&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Carney gives a long explanation of forward guidance (which began by not promising to raise rates until unemployment fell below 7%). He says these pledges helped to underpin confidence and support the economy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/BOE?src=hash"&gt;#BOE&lt;/a&gt; Gov Mark &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Carney?src=hash"&gt;#Carney&lt;/a&gt; confirms interest rates can now go up or down: "neutral bias: monetary policy is appropriate" &lt;a href="https://t.co/DdIrd2Kc05"&gt;https://t.co/DdIrd2Kc05&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-15T10:53:34.981Z"&gt;10.53am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Tyrie mischievously turns Carney’s attention over the Atlantic, suggesting that Donald Trump and Theresa May share the same concerns over central banks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q: Trump has been “pretty critical of the Fed”, hasn’t he?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It’s very important to distinguish between the stance of monetary policy and the reasons why global interest rates are low, the reasons why inequality has increased across major economics.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Those are caused by much more fundamental factors. And an excessive focus on monetary policy in many respects is a massive blame deflection exercise.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Mark Carney says those politicians complaining about low rates from central banks are engaged in a "massive blame deflection exercise"...&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-15T10:47:26.565Z"&gt;10.47am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q: Do you think that the fact that central banks are responsible for such a huge range of activities today puts you in a position where you are more vulnerable to criticism, such as over Brexit?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Carney plays this ball safely.&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-15T10:44:44.852Z"&gt;10.44am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q: Did Theresa May’s apparent criticism of central banks in her recent conference speech influence your decision to only serve another 12 months?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;No, Carney replies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-15T10:37:06.387Z"&gt;10.37am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mark Carney denies that the uncertainty over his departure date has created uncertainty.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are “far bigger issues’ in the UK economy, and the global economy, than my term lengths, he says.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-15T10:35:11.083Z"&gt;10.35am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mark Carney’s grilling at the Treasury Committee is underway.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Chairman Andrew Tyrie asks the Bank of England governor how much uncertainty has been caused by his decision to initially only serve five years, and then extend it by 12 months. &lt;em&gt;Wouldn’t it be better to keep governors to fixed terms of eight years?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-15T10:20:58.771Z"&gt;10.20am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;While we wait for Mr Carney, there’s time to flag up that UK house prices rose by 7.7% in the 12 months to September.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;That matches August’s reading, with houses in the south of England driving the market up.&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;UK house prices grew at a healthy 7.7%y/y clip in September. East of England led the way with 12.1%y/y growth while N. East at only 1.5%y/y. &lt;a href="https://t.co/LSet77CLtj"&gt;pic.twitter.com/LSet77CLtj&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“We now have three months of post-Brexit official housing figures, which show price growth remaining robust, but fewer properties changing hands. At the start of the year, we expected slower house price growth, but in fact it has shown impressive resilience: in the first three quarters of the year average annual house prices were up by around 8% across the UK compared to the same period last year.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“But high prices are causing some buyers to stay out of the market altogether. The ONS data show residential transactions in September were just 93,000, 11.3% lower than the previous year. This implies that underlying demand may be weakening as property becomes less and less affordable.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-15T10:14:34.212Z"&gt;10.14am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bank of England governor Mark Carney is due to give evidence to the Treasury Committee in parliament now, on the Bank’s latest quarterly inflation report.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.parliamentlive.tv/Event/Index/074e655b-c7db-4f9e-985d-b561784099a1"&gt;There’s a livefeed here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-15T10:11:13.406Z"&gt;10.11am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Newsflash from Brussels: the eurozone economy grew by 0.3% in the third quarter of this year, matching Q2’s growth rate.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Although Germany and France only grew by 0.2%, Italy expanded by 0.3% and the Netherlands and Spain both posted healthy growth of 0.7%.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Euro area GDP +0.3% in Q3 2016, +1.6% compared with Q3 2015 &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Eurostat?src=hash"&gt;#Eurostat&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;a href="https://t.co/IYKjKoK4hg"&gt;https://t.co/IYKjKoK4hg&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://t.co/ELfGUzo4PN"&gt;pic.twitter.com/ELfGUzo4PN&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-15T10:04:26.178Z"&gt;10.04am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A string of economist are predicting that Britain’s inflation rate will keep rising in the months ahead, despite &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/live/2016/nov/15/german-growth-uk-inflation-mark-carney-bond-market-obama-greece-business-live?page=with:block-582ad3e1e4b05c05c52f5269#block-582ad3e1e4b05c05c52f5269"&gt;dropping to 0.9% in October&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tom Stevenson, investment director for personal investing at Fidelity International, says&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“The expected rise in inflation paused for breath today as higher fuel prices were offset by slower rises in the price of clothes and university fees and cheaper hotel stays.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Against all expectations, the CPI rose by just 0.9% in the year to October, slightly lower than September’s 1% increase. However prices are still rising faster than at any time since late 2014. The rise in prices continue to be driven by sterling’s recent weakness which has raised the cost of imported fuel and food.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In our estimates it will be the early part of the New Year that sees the majority of the price rises. Retailers are some of the smartest companies out there and they know it would be suicide to hike prices now pre-Christmas.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Of course, the tightness of budgets in the retail environment means that any price rises are going to be painful – and low cost operators and discounters will be ready to pounce - but they will have to come or we will likely see additional seasonal and structural unemployment increases in 2017.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;No use talking about inflation now IMO. It will be the New Year that sees the price rises as retailers cave to input pressures.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;While inflation eased last month there is a ticking time bomb in the PPI data, which measures the costs of goods for manufacturers. And here there is a sign that much higher consumer inflation is on its way.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ONS data showed factory gate prices for goods produced by UK manufacturers rose 2.1% in the year to October 2016, which was a sharp jump from the 1.3% in the year to September 2016.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Oct surge in &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/UK?src=hash"&gt;#UK&lt;/a&gt; producer input &amp;amp; output &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/prices?src=hash"&gt;#prices&lt;/a&gt; suggest dip seen in consumer price &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/inflation?src=hash"&gt;#inflation&lt;/a&gt; to 0.9% in Oct will prove a brief respite&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-15T09:57:40.138Z"&gt;9.57am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We shouldn’t get carried away by &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/live/2016/nov/15/german-growth-uk-inflation-mark-carney-bond-market-obama-greece-business-live?page=with:block-582ad3e1e4b05c05c52f5269#block-582ad3e1e4b05c05c52f5269"&gt;this inflation slowdown&lt;/a&gt; - it will surely only be temporary.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The detail of today’s report shows that Britain’s CPI rate dipped last month because clothing prices had jumped sharply a year earlier, in October 2015.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clothing and footwear: the downward effect came mainly from garments (in particular women’s outerwear), for which prices rose by 0.2% between September and October 2016, compared with a larger rise of 2.3% a year earlie&lt;/strong&gt;r. It is important to note that this followed a relatively large increase in prices in September 2016, which resulted in an upward contribution to the change in the rate of a similar magnitude to the downward effect seen in October. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Education: charges, overall, rose by 2.0% between September and October this year compared with a larger rise of 3.6% between the same 2 months a year ago&lt;/strong&gt;. The downward contribution came principally from UK and EU student tuition fees, where the impact from the rise in the cap for tuition fees (first introduced for new students in England in 2012) was smaller this year than in 2015. This was because nearly all students are already paying the higher rate of fees whereas last year the fees for fourth year courses rose to the higher rates. In addition there were more modest price increases for part-time and postgraduate fees compared with last year.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-15T09:51:23.054Z"&gt;9.51am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Today’s figures also show that Britain’s manufacturers are suffering from a hefty dose of inflation, due to the weak pound.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Britain’s Producer Prices index spiked by 4.6% in October - the biggest monthly rise on record.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;UK inflation posts surprise fall in October, but watch this space. Producer prices for raw material &amp;amp; oil +4.6%, biggest monthly rise ever.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Weak inflation this month. But higher prices incoming. ONS says imported goods prices up 14.1% in yr to Sep. Biggest increase since Sep 2011&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-15T09:46:15.120Z"&gt;9.46am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This chart shows how Britain’s CPI rate dipped, after jumping in September:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-15T09:38:32.209Z"&gt;9.38am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The pound is falling sharply, as traders react to today’s inflation report.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sterling has lost three-quarters of a cent, to $1.241 against the US dollar.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Pound falls against dollar after CPI inflation rate unexpectedly drops to 0.9% &lt;a href="https://t.co/DvOCJLkTMI"&gt;https://t.co/DvOCJLkTMI&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://t.co/uK3NyYv78Z"&gt;pic.twitter.com/uK3NyYv78Z&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-15T09:36:25.192Z"&gt;9.36am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Office for National Statistics says cheaper clothing helped to drive the UK inflation rate down last month, countering a rise in fuel costs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The main downward contributors to the change in the rate were prices for clothing and university tuition fees, which rose by less than they did a year ago, along with falling prices for certain games and toys, overnight hotel stays and non-alcoholic beverages.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;These downward pressures were offset by rising prices for motor fuels, and by prices for furniture and furnishings, which fell by less than they did a year ago.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-15T09:31:44.887Z"&gt;9.31am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Breaking! Britain’s inflation rate has fallen!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The consumer prices index only rose by 0.9% in October, new figures show, compared with 1.0% in September.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-15T09:20:50.714Z"&gt;9.20am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Here’s Fiona Cincotta of City Index explaining why &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/live/2016/nov/15/german-growth-uk-inflation-mark-carney-bond-market-obama-greece-business-live?page=with:block-582ad141e4b05c05c52f525c#block-582ad141e4b05c05c52f525c"&gt;the bond market rout has taken a break this morning&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The turmoil in the bond market appears to be pausing for breath, which is quite typical after the moves we have seen. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The global bond market has sold off at an extraordinary rate since Trump won the presidential race 6 days ago and is currently on track for its worst monthly decline since 2003.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-15T09:18:23.158Z"&gt;9.18am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The bond markets are calmer this morning, as investors take a breather after several days of falls.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Government bond prices have recovered in early trading, pulling yields down from yesterday’s highs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-15T09:08:30.640Z"&gt;9.08am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Good news from Italy! Its economy has returned to growth, with GDP expanding by 0.3% in the last quarter.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;That means the Italian economy has beaten expectations - and beaten Germany, whose 0.2% growth rate looks even more sluggish now.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Italy GDP Growth Rate &lt;a href="https://t.co/XebmdJYjsO"&gt;https://t.co/XebmdJYjsO&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://t.co/qYFZoDmVTc"&gt;pic.twitter.com/qYFZoDmVTc&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Italian GDP expanded by 0.3% QoQ in Q3. Not exactly booming, but still better than expected.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/fwred"&gt;@fwred&lt;/a&gt; and all the more welcome as is the only one to (just) beat forecasts among all the Europe Q3 GDP data today&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Italian GDP rises 0.3 per cent in the third quarter, beating expectations - boost for Renzi pre-referendum&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;The latest polls show the 'No' in the Italian referendum extending lead to 5%+. Given pollsters' performance I guess there's still a chance. &lt;a href="https://t.co/jw7KAdMKjc"&gt;pic.twitter.com/jw7KAdMKjc&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-15T08:54:24.965Z"&gt;8.54am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Just in! The Netherlands has beaten Germany, by posting growth of 0.7% in the third quarter of the year:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Boom! Netherlands GDP 0.7% g/q, 2.4% y/y! Although housing investment still high, growth primarily driven by household consumption &amp;amp; exports &lt;a href="https://t.co/6oYmOzWPP6"&gt;pic.twitter.com/6oYmOzWPP6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-15T08:52:37.134Z"&gt;8.52am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Economists are blaming Germany’s slowdown on the impact of Britain’s vote to leave the EU.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The slump in the pound since June has made German goods less competitive in Britain, and also dented confidence across the global economy. So this would explain why exports fell between July and September, &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/live/2016/nov/15/german-growth-uk-inflation-mark-carney-bond-market-obama-greece-business-live?page=with:block-582ab77be4b05c05c52f51fe#block-582ab77be4b05c05c52f51fe"&gt;pulling German growth down to 0.2%&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Brexit meets solid domestic economy. This is probably the best description of the German economic performance during the third quarter.” &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“If Germany’s single most important trading partner, the U.S., really moves towards more protectionism, this would definitely leave its mark on German growth.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“One had expected a little more economic activity in the third quarter. But the signs for the final quarter are looking good.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-15T08:36:52.459Z"&gt;8.36am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Not so good for Germany as GDP only increased by 0.2% in the 3rd quarter &lt;a href="https://t.co/sY6yrXu5Kr"&gt;https://t.co/sY6yrXu5Kr&lt;/a&gt; Imagine if the UK had done that!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-15T08:30:30.440Z"&gt;8.30am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Europe’s stock markets are mainly creeping higher this morning:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-15T08:22:48.527Z"&gt;8.22am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Britain’s FTSE 100 index has jumped by 46 point at the start of trading.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Supermarket group Tesco has jumped by 3%, after new data shows sales growing at their fastest rate since 2013:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Tesco benefits from fastest sales growth in three years: &lt;a href="https://t.co/swFqRW29i3"&gt;https://t.co/swFqRW29i3&lt;/a&gt; Grocery share data from our &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/KWP_UK"&gt;@KWP_UK&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/grocery?src=hash"&gt;#grocery&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/data?src=hash"&gt;#data&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Tesco?src=hash"&gt;#Tesco&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://t.co/ZBHReFMig8"&gt;pic.twitter.com/ZBHReFMig8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Kantar data boosts supermarkets: Wm Morrison (+3.3%) Tesco (+3%). Sainsbury (+2.6%) &lt;a href="https://t.co/zVV9dmX1HR"&gt;https://t.co/zVV9dmX1HR&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-15T08:14:59.884Z"&gt;8.14am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jeroen Blokland of &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Robeco"&gt;Robeco Asset Management&lt;/a&gt; is also concerned that Germany’s economy has faltered:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Uh-oh, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Germany?src=hash"&gt;#Germany&lt;/a&gt;'s &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/GDP?src=hash"&gt;#GDP&lt;/a&gt; growth disappoints at 0.2% in Q3, slowest in a year. &lt;a href="https://t.co/iDEIFiJubA"&gt;pic.twitter.com/iDEIFiJubA&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-15T07:59:05.209Z"&gt;7.59am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Analysts at Citi reckon Germany’s economy suffered from the shock of Britain’s vote to leave the EU:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Acc to Citi, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Brexit?src=hash"&gt;#Brexit&lt;/a&gt; uncertainty is to blame for German GDP growth slowdown. "&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Germany?src=hash"&gt;#Germany&lt;/a&gt; did experience significant spill-over from UK shock." &lt;a href="https://t.co/KdfUzr3vEA"&gt;pic.twitter.com/KdfUzr3vEA&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-15T07:54:20.699Z"&gt;7.54am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/live/2016/nov/15/german-growth-uk-inflation-mark-carney-bond-market-obama-greece-business-live?page=with:block-582ab77be4b05c05c52f51fe#block-582ab77be4b05c05c52f51fe"&gt;Germany’s weak performance&lt;/a&gt; may drag down the wider eurozone growth rate, which is published at 10am.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Figures released earlier this month suggested euro area GDP expanded by 0.3%, but &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/HolgerSandte"&gt;Holger Sandte&lt;/a&gt; of Nordea Markets fears that could be too optimistic.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;German &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/GDP?src=hash"&gt;#GDP&lt;/a&gt; growth of 0.2% q/q in Q3 makes 0.3 for the Euro area pretty likely&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Rollercoaster ride ends with a soft landing. German GDP growth slows down to 0.2% QoQ in third quarter.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Germany?src=hash"&gt;#Germany&lt;/a&gt; disappoints. GDP grew by 0.2% QoQ in Q3 vs 0.3% expected &amp;amp; down from 0.4% in Q2 &amp;amp; 0.7% in Q1 as net exports contributes negatively. &lt;a href="https://t.co/kFgh13xEgN"&gt;pic.twitter.com/kFgh13xEgN&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-15T07:33:00.950Z"&gt;7.33am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bad news: Germany’s economy has suffered a surprise slowdown, with growth halving in the last three months as foreign trade waned.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The eurozone’s largest economy only expanded by 0.2% in the third quarter of this year, figures just released show. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Foreign trade had a downward effect on growth. Exports were slightly down while imports were slightly up compared with the second quarter of 2016.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="block-time published-time"&gt; &lt;time datetime="2016-11-15T07:17:26.637Z"&gt;7.17am &lt;span class="timezone"&gt;GMT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/time&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Good morning, and welcome to our rolling coverage of the world economy, the financial market, the eurozone and business.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There’s lots happening today, both in the financial world and the markets.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fears about the inflationary potential of &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/donaldtrump"&gt;Donald Trump&lt;/a&gt;’s planned tax cuts and infrastructure spending have sent shock waves through the world’s bond markets, as investors take fright at the prospect of higher than expected interest rates in the years ahead.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Central banks are braced to suffer fresh losses on their vast holdings of government debt after the sell-off that saw $1tn wiped off the value of bonds last week intensified on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;span&gt;Related: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/2016/nov/14/bonds-trump-prompts-inflation-tax-cuts-interest-rates"&gt;Global bonds slump as Trump prompts inflation fears&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;span&gt;Related: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2016/nov/13/barack-obama-calls-for-meaningful-debt-relief-for-greece"&gt;Barack Obama calls for 'meaningful debt relief' for Greece&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Athens locked down as police focus on terror concerns during Obama visit &lt;a href="https://t.co/VKFX5OU65b"&gt;https://t.co/VKFX5OU65b&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://t.co/xs379IVZxo"&gt;pic.twitter.com/xs379IVZxo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/live/2016/nov/15/german-growth-uk-inflation-mark-carney-bond-market-obama-greece-business-live"&gt;Continue reading...&lt;/a&gt;</description>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/business">Business</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/world/germany">Germany</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/inflation">Inflation</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/mark-carney">Mark Carney</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/barack-obama">Barack Obama</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/world/greece">Greece</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/economics">Economics</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/stock-markets">Stock markets</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Nov 2016 18:11:15 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.theguardian.com/business/live/2016/nov/15/german-growth-uk-inflation-mark-carney-bond-market-obama-greece-business-live</guid>
      <media:content width="140" url="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/0f247ea3586f5cb4e451a465ab802ef856048cab/0_33_1544_926/master/1544.jpg?w=140&amp;q=55&amp;auto=format&amp;usm=12&amp;fit=max&amp;s=f0ab70bccb2ab851fcfa333a46079ee8">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Photograph: PA</media:credit>
      </media:content>
      <media:content width="460" url="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/0f247ea3586f5cb4e451a465ab802ef856048cab/0_33_1544_926/master/1544.jpg?w=460&amp;q=55&amp;auto=format&amp;usm=12&amp;fit=max&amp;s=0f143ae3da0d216c398cd226d4529e89">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Photograph: PA</media:credit>
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>Graeme Wearden (until 2.15pm GMT) and Nick Fletcher (now)</dc:creator>
      <dc:date>2016-11-15T18:11:15Z</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Brexit? I've no idea what's going on either, says Mark Carney</title>
      <link>https://www.theguardian.com/business/2016/nov/15/mark-carney-bank-of-england-brexit-treasury-select-committee</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Once bitten, twice shy is the phrase that comes to mind as the Bank of England governor appears before MPs&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The governor of the Bank of England &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/2016/may/24/bank-of-england-governor-rejects-accusations-of-bias-over-eu-referendum"&gt;took a lot of flak&lt;/a&gt; during the EU referendum campaign for &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/2016/may/12/bank-of-england-keeps-interest-rates-on-hold-as-brexit-fears-bite"&gt;forecasting an economic downturn&lt;/a&gt; in the event of a Brexit vote, so he was hellbent on giving away as little information as possible at his latest appearance before the Treasury select committee. See no evil, hear no evil, speak no evil.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“I may be a bit thick,” said the Conservative Kit Malthouse, a newcomer to the committee, “but can you explain what exactly forward guidance is?”&lt;/p&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/2016/nov/15/mark-carney-bank-of-england-brexit-treasury-select-committee"&gt;Continue reading...&lt;/a&gt;</description>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/mark-carney">Mark Carney</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/politics">Politics</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/uk/uk">UK news</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/bankofenglandgovernor">Bank of England</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/business">Business</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/houseofcommons">House of Commons</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/inflation">Inflation</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/eu-referendum">EU referendum and Brexit</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/economics">Economics</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Nov 2016 17:39:09 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.theguardian.com/business/2016/nov/15/mark-carney-bank-of-england-brexit-treasury-select-committee</guid>
      <media:content width="140" url="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/c73c7decb233735965f44fee5ecd442c21811f0f/0_0_1536_922/master/1536.jpg?w=140&amp;q=55&amp;auto=format&amp;usm=12&amp;fit=max&amp;s=fb1cca41508cc0570fae2f823eb5e973">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Photograph: PA</media:credit>
      </media:content>
      <media:content width="460" url="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/c73c7decb233735965f44fee5ecd442c21811f0f/0_0_1536_922/master/1536.jpg?w=460&amp;q=55&amp;auto=format&amp;usm=12&amp;fit=max&amp;s=29c19af7996003deec26a74bb97858cb">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Photograph: PA</media:credit>
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>John Crace</dc:creator>
      <dc:date>2016-11-15T17:39:09Z</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ireland must plan for possible EU breakup, says economic adviser</title>
      <link>https://www.theguardian.com/world/2016/nov/15/ireland-draft-plan-eu-breakup-frexit</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Sean Barrett calls on government of Enda Kenny to support France’s attempts to win concessions from Brussels to stop a ‘Frexit’&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ireland should be drawing up contingency plans for the EU unravelling after Brexit and a possible French departure, an economic adviser to successive Irish governments has said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dr Sean Barrett urged Enda Kenny’s administration in Dublin to strongly back any French attempt to gain more concessions from Brussels to &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2016/jul/20/well-done-britain-brexit-vote-boosts-french-far-right-front-national-election-machine"&gt;prevent a possible “Frexit”&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;span&gt;Related: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2016/nov/12/elections-eu-donald-trump-brexit-italy-referendum"&gt;Marine Le Pen, Beppe Grillo, Geert Wilders, Frauke Petry: has their big moment arrived?&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;span&gt;Related: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/2016/jun/27/frexit-nexit-or-oexit-who-will-be-next-to-leave-the-eu"&gt;Frexit, Nexit or Oexit? Who will be next to leave the EU&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;span&gt;Related: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2016/sep/02/angela-merkel-marine-le-pen-europe-destiny"&gt;Angela Merkel and Marine Le Pen: one of them will shape Europe’s future | Natalie Nougayrède&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2016/nov/15/ireland-draft-plan-eu-breakup-frexit"&gt;Continue reading...&lt;/a&gt;</description>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/world/ireland">Ireland</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/eu-referendum">EU referendum and Brexit</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/world/europe-news">Europe</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/world/eu">European Union</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/politics">Politics</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/world/enda-kenny">Enda Kenny</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/euro">Euro</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/business">Business</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/currencies">Currencies</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/economics">Economics</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/world/marine-le-pen">Marine Le Pen</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/world/france">France</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/european-central-bank">European Central Bank</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/foreignpolicy">Foreign policy</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/world/world">World news</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Nov 2016 14:39:07 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.theguardian.com/world/2016/nov/15/ireland-draft-plan-eu-breakup-frexit</guid>
      <media:content width="140" url="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/93cca7e83887b128543c5c710367c308fa9bd1a3/0_161_4928_2957/master/4928.jpg?w=140&amp;q=55&amp;auto=format&amp;usm=12&amp;fit=max&amp;s=07bc81f34b2dcccef2d4c30f0df1c9eb">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Photograph: Clodagh Kilcoyne/Reuters</media:credit>
      </media:content>
      <media:content width="460" url="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/93cca7e83887b128543c5c710367c308fa9bd1a3/0_161_4928_2957/master/4928.jpg?w=460&amp;q=55&amp;auto=format&amp;usm=12&amp;fit=max&amp;s=73f051cd9fbe0624d77225a336537357">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Photograph: Clodagh Kilcoyne/Reuters</media:credit>
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>Henry McDonald Ireland correspondent</dc:creator>
      <dc:date>2016-11-15T14:39:07Z</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Joseph Stiglitz: what the US economy needs from Donald Trump</title>
      <link>https://www.theguardian.com/business/2016/nov/15/joseph-stiglitz-what-the-us-economy-needs-from-donald-trump</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Too many Americans feel left behind by globalisation. But Trump is unlikely to pursue the agenda his voters need. This is what he should do&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Donald Trump’s astonishing victory in the US presidential election has made one thing abundantly clear: too many Americans – particularly white male Americans – feel left behind. It is not just a feeling, it can be seen in the data no less clearly than in their anger. And, as I have argued repeatedly, an economic system that doesn’t deliver for large parts of the population is a failed economic system. So what should President-elect Trump do about it?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Over the past third of a century, the rules of America’s economic system have been rewritten in ways that serve a few at the top, while harming the economy as a whole, and especially the bottom 80%. The irony of Trump’s victory is that it was the Republican party he now leads that pushed for extreme globalisation and against the policy frameworks that would have mitigated the trauma associated with it. But history matters: China and India are now integrated into the global economy. Besides, technology has been advancing so fast that the number of jobs globally in manufacturing is declining.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;span&gt;Related: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/2016/nov/15/trumpism-solution-crisis-neoliberalism-robert-skidelsky"&gt;Trumpism could be a solution to the crisis of neoliberalism&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;span&gt;Related: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/2016/nov/11/oval-office-will-tame-us-president-donald-trump"&gt;The Oval Office will tame President Donald Trump&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/2016/nov/15/joseph-stiglitz-what-the-us-economy-needs-from-donald-trump"&gt;Continue reading...&lt;/a&gt;</description>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/business">Business</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/useconomy">US economy</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/economics">Economics</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/donaldtrump">Donald Trump</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/us-news">US news</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/environment/climate-change">Climate change</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/environment/carbon-emissions">Greenhouse gas emissions</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/global-economy">Global economy</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Nov 2016 12:00:15 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.theguardian.com/business/2016/nov/15/joseph-stiglitz-what-the-us-economy-needs-from-donald-trump</guid>
      <media:content width="140" url="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/596982f9b229f136995c02226df38c0143a4d91a/0_235_5118_3071/master/5118.jpg?w=140&amp;q=55&amp;auto=format&amp;usm=12&amp;fit=max&amp;s=51bfd8cd8d8b24252b640140e69be5be">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Photograph: JGI/Jamie Grill/Getty Images/Blend Images</media:credit>
      </media:content>
      <media:content width="460" url="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/596982f9b229f136995c02226df38c0143a4d91a/0_235_5118_3071/master/5118.jpg?w=460&amp;q=55&amp;auto=format&amp;usm=12&amp;fit=max&amp;s=6d23831e49c015256cd8d0de965248cd">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Photograph: JGI/Jamie Grill/Getty Images/Blend Images</media:credit>
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>Joseph Stiglitz</dc:creator>
      <dc:date>2016-11-15T12:00:15Z</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trumpism could be a solution to the crisis of neoliberalism</title>
      <link>https://www.theguardian.com/business/2016/nov/15/trumpism-solution-crisis-neoliberalism-robert-skidelsky</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There is Keynesian merit in Trump’s policies which challenge the neoliberal obsession with deficits and debt reduction. Liberals need to question and refine the plan, not dismiss it as ignorant ravings&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Republican establishment has gone into overdrive to present President-elect Donald Trump as a guarantor of continuity. Of course, he is nothing of the sort. He campaigned against the political establishment, and, &lt;a href="http://www.bloomberg.com/politics/videos/2016-11-07/donald-trump-election-will-be-brexit-plus-plus-plus"&gt;as he told a pre-election rally, a victory for him would be a “Brexit plus, plus, plus”.&lt;/a&gt; With two political earthquakes within months of each other, and more sure to follow, we may well agree with the &lt;a href="http://foreignpolicy.com/2016/11/09/the-world-as-we-know-it-is-crumbling-before-our-eyes/"&gt;verdict of France’s ambassador to the United States: the world as we know it “is crumbling before our eyes”.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The last time this seemed to be happening was the era of the two world wars, 1914 to 1945. The sense then of a “crumbling” world was captured by WB Yeats’s 1919 poem The Second Coming: “Things fall apart; the centre cannot hold;/Mere anarchy is loosed upon the world.” With the traditional institutions of rule thoroughly discredited by the war, the vacuum of legitimacy would be filled by powerful demagogues and populist dictatorships: “The best lack all conviction, while the worst/are full of passionate intensity.” Oswald Spengler had the same idea in his Decline of the West, published in 1918.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;span&gt;Related: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/economics-blog/2016/nov/13/donald-trump-product-of-new-economic-depression"&gt;We are living in a depression - that's why Trump took the White House&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The second coming of liberalism represented by Roosevelt, Keynes, and the founders of the European Union has been destroyed by the economics of globalisation: the pursuit of an ideal equilibrium through the free movement of goods, capital, and labour, with its conjoined tolerance of financial criminality, obscenely lavish rewards for a few, high levels of unemployment and underemployment, and curtailment of the state’s role in welfare provision. The resulting inequality of economic outcomes strips away the democratic veil that hides from the majority of citizens the true workings of power.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;span&gt;Related: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2016/nov/14/neoliberalsim-donald-trump-george-monbiot"&gt;Neoliberalism: the deep story that lies beneath Donald Trump’s triumph | George Monbiot&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/2016/nov/15/trumpism-solution-crisis-neoliberalism-robert-skidelsky"&gt;Continue reading...&lt;/a&gt;</description>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/economics">Economics</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/global-economy">Global economy</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/business">Business</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/donaldtrump">Donald Trump</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/eu-referendum">EU referendum and Brexit</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/politics">Politics</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/us-news">US news</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Nov 2016 08:17:32 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.theguardian.com/business/2016/nov/15/trumpism-solution-crisis-neoliberalism-robert-skidelsky</guid>
      <media:content width="140" url="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/f3de3e75d65abe07707cfe8d7e81c258b5701983/0_263_5184_3111/master/5184.jpg?w=140&amp;q=55&amp;auto=format&amp;usm=12&amp;fit=max&amp;s=a1625c7cc1f7719acf39f28b31204d65">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Photograph: Petros Giannakouris/AP</media:credit>
      </media:content>
      <media:content width="460" url="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/f3de3e75d65abe07707cfe8d7e81c258b5701983/0_263_5184_3111/master/5184.jpg?w=460&amp;q=55&amp;auto=format&amp;usm=12&amp;fit=max&amp;s=ca0cee3225424f5438e79e2286b5e2fc">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Photograph: Petros Giannakouris/AP</media:credit>
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>Robert Skidelsky</dc:creator>
      <dc:date>2016-11-15T08:17:32Z</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rust-belt romantics don’t get it: the middle class is being wiped out too | Aditya Chakrabortty</title>
      <link>https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2016/nov/15/rust-belt-middle-class-wiped-out</link>
      <description>Look carefully and it is clear that rapacious capitalism has all of us - not just the working class  - in its sights&lt;p&gt;At least now you know who to blame. Since &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/eu-referendum"&gt;Brexit&lt;/a&gt; and especially after Donald Trump, the quack analysts have been out in force, holding aloft their quack explanations. It is apparently all the fault of the white working classes. They got left behind and cast aside in the past two decades of globalisation – now they’re making the rest of us pay.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;span&gt;Related: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/sustainable-business/2016/nov/14/no-politician-can-keep-a-promise-to-bring-back-jobs-especially-not-donald-trump"&gt;No politician can keep a promise to bring back jobs – especially not Donald Trump&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2016/nov/15/rust-belt-middle-class-wiped-out"&gt;Continue reading...&lt;/a&gt;</description>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/world/globalisation">Globalisation</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/austerity">Austerity</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/donaldtrump">Donald Trump</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/eu-referendum">EU referendum and Brexit</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/economics">Economics</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/society/society">Society</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/uk/uk">UK news</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/us-news">US news</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/world/world">World news</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Nov 2016 07:00:10 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2016/nov/15/rust-belt-middle-class-wiped-out</guid>
      <media:content width="140" url="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/b2cc34bbe9f62352364985c3be88d291d6335a28/0_202_3500_2100/master/3500.jpg?w=140&amp;q=55&amp;auto=format&amp;usm=12&amp;fit=max&amp;s=8fcf79244a602214a3c60cc78fc04277">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Photograph: Mark Makela/Getty Images</media:credit>
      </media:content>
      <media:content width="460" url="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/b2cc34bbe9f62352364985c3be88d291d6335a28/0_202_3500_2100/master/3500.jpg?w=460&amp;q=55&amp;auto=format&amp;usm=12&amp;fit=max&amp;s=0489390cadd5455979335654c6e5c8ab">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Photograph: Mark Makela/Getty Images</media:credit>
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>Aditya Chakrabortty</dc:creator>
      <dc:date>2016-11-15T07:00:10Z</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>'Temporary factors' behind Australia's recent economic growth spurt, IMF says</title>
      <link>https://www.theguardian.com/business/2016/nov/15/temporary-factors-behind-australias-recent-economic-growth-spurt-imf-says</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Annual review of the Australian economy also criticises rise in underemployment and longer-term unemployment &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Australian economy could expect a stronger performance if the recent improvement in the terms of trade boosts business confidence and unlocks investment, the International Monetary Fund said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The IMF said Australia’s economic performance had remained remarkable compared with other countries, but warns there was a downside risk to the outlook if investment remained subdued should company profits remain under pressure for longer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;span&gt;Related: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2016/nov/15/harping-on-about-economic-growth-makes-politicians-seem-out-of-touch"&gt;Harping on about economic growth makes politicians seem out of touch | Greg Jericho&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/2016/nov/15/temporary-factors-behind-australias-recent-economic-growth-spurt-imf-says"&gt;Continue reading...&lt;/a&gt;</description>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/australia-economy">Australian economy</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/australia-news/australia-news">Australia news</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/imf">International Monetary Fund (IMF)</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/australia-news/business-australia">Business in Australia</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/economics">Economics</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/australia-news/interest-rates-australia">Interest rates Australia</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/australia-news/australian-politics">Australian politics</category>
      <category domain="https://www.theguardian.com/business/global-economy">Global economy</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Nov 2016 06:53:57 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.theguardian.com/business/2016/nov/15/temporary-factors-behind-australias-recent-economic-growth-spurt-imf-says</guid>
      <media:content width="140" url="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/df088563fc193959df345f7f8836bc5b7574b64c/0_0_4096_2457/master/4096.jpg?w=140&amp;q=55&amp;auto=format&amp;usm=12&amp;fit=max&amp;s=78e11aef39c813b48d8b943361c25791">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Photograph: Dean Lewins/EPA</media:credit>
      </media:content>
      <media:content width="460" url="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/df088563fc193959df345f7f8836bc5b7574b64c/0_0_4096_2457/master/4096.jpg?w=460&amp;q=55&amp;auto=format&amp;usm=12&amp;fit=max&amp;s=ecce0a6ad4362ec6eee539c771ce51a1">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Photograph: Dean Lewins/EPA</media:credit>
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>Staff and agencies</dc:creator>
      <dc:date>2016-11-15T06:53:57Z</dc:date>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>